hello and welcome everyone this is the
third applied octave inference Symposium
enacting ecosystems of shared
intelligence it is August 22nd 2023
we have a lot of really awesome
presentations and sessions coming up in
the
first interval and in the second
interval so let's just get right into it
with our first talk this will be by
Andre bastos so Andre thank you for
joining and looking forward to your talk
thank you very well Daniel and thank you
for the other organizers of the active
inference uh conference and Symposium
here I'm glad to be talking to you guys
today about my work it's the title of
the presentation is multi-laminer
multi-area recordings under non-human
primate that's these guys right here in
CAC monkeys suggests that predictive
coding is implemented by a predictive
routing and so what do we mean by these
things well uh just as a point of
introduction I'd like to I'd like to
start by just saying that
um we we started out uh I started out
working with with Carl Tristan in about
2010 and we were really interested in
trying to map the neurobiology of the
predictive coding circuits that have
that have been theorized and
hypothesized onto cortical laminar
architecture which you can see here and
uh in in that work with him we proposed
that different layers and different
oscillations were involved in either
capturing and calculating prediction
error or predictions and so what what we
do in my lab and I recently started as
an assistant professor in the department
of psychology at Vanderbilt and so what
we do is we train rhesus macaque monkeys
on on tasks which are more or less
predictable and that have have different
sensory elements that are more or less
predictable and we'll get into what that
looks like and then we use multi-laminar
probes so high density probes with
dozens or hundreds of contacts that can
record across different layers and so
this is a beautiful drawing here of what
what the layers look like of Cortex by
Santiago ramonica Hall over 100 years
ago and you can see this really
beautiful layer layered architecture
layer one two three four is this dense
one in the middle five you get these
large pyramidal neurons and then six on
the bottom and so we're interested in in
my lab and primarily at two levels of
explanation the first is what do these
neurons Spike to what makes them fire
Action potentials and excites them and
do they get more or less excitable
depending on how predictable stimuli are
and second how do they oscillate and
which frequency bands do those rhythmic
activity tend to cause them to fire more
or less action potentials and so we
record across layers in one area over
here but we might put in our electrodes
and several other areas so that we can
also capture aspects of cortical
communication and these oscillations in
this communication we think is is really
intimately linked to the interaction
between inhibitory cells these cells in
red here and excitatory neurons these
these cells in Black that are doing okay
so without further Ado let's just dive
right into it here
so here's the outline of my talk in part
one we're going to be talking about
first an overview of what do we actually
mean by this predictive coding model and
how do we think it it may be mapped onto
cortex and paying special attention to
the neurophysiology so here's the bird's
eye overview of predictive coding at the
level that maybe a neurobiologist or a
cognitive scientist or a
um or a cognitive neuroscientist might
need to know about in order to be able
to uh to apply it to to their own work
and so here's uh here's what I mean by
predictive coding that there's a
hypothesized circuit that is especially
rich in higher order areas so here's
like the front of the brain which learns
about the statistical regularities of
the world and creates predictions about
what is going to be seen and felt and
touched and so on in the next moment in
time and in this moment in time and
sends those predictions to earlier parts
of the brain so it's a lower order
cortex receive these predictions and
sensory inputs the inputs coming from
the eyes and ears and all of our
sensorium has been compared to this
top-down prediction and if there's a
mismatch that's a prediction error and
the prediction error is fed forward it's
in this match response and it can be
used to drive models Drive these
internal representations in order to be
better over time and to make better
predictions and in particular the these
prediction errors are hypothesized to be
housed in superficial layers of Cortex
and so that's a that's a hypothesis that
we've been able to test now with these
laminar electrons so let's see how our
experimental design worked in order for
us to be able to look at the difference
between predictable and unpredictable
sensory stimuli so we train monkeys on
what's called a delayed match to sample
tasks it's a classic task of working
memory where monkeys are trained to
fixate on the center of the screen then
there's a visual stimulus in this case a
car stimulus that's shown there's a
brief delay in which that stimulus has
to be held in working memory when the
animal is tested on which of the three
items was in working memory the animal
makes a correct response when they
cicada in this case to the upper left to
indicate that the car stimulus was last
shown
so we we then manipulated the
predictability of this information that
was to enter working memory in the
following way for 50 trials in a row we
would either keep the sample stimulus uh
constant so car car and that's being
depicted by the a here or in another
context there would be an unpredictable
sampling regime where either the car
orange or green could be sampled at any
moment in time so the animals went back
and forth in being in a predictable
context or an unpredictable context and
then we asked the question what does
grain activity look like when the exact
same stimulus is processed in a
predictable regime versus an
unpredictable regime
and in order to do this work we
implanted these monkeys with
multi-laminar probe so these are probes
again with these at that time uh that I
did this work about a dozen or so or
maybe up to 32 contacts nowadays we can
go into the several hundreds of contacts
along a single probe we can use MRI
guidance in order to position those
probes perpendicular to Cortex such that
they'll span each of the six cortical
layers that are one through six here you
can see the white matter here below and
then we sampled from different parts of
both the visual cortex because remember
those are the areas that might issue
prediction errors in the face of an
unpredictable sample as well as higher
order cortex which has been hypothesized
to create these internal models that
have been issue predictions
so here's what we found we first just
analyzed the multi-unit activity which
is a measure of the spike rate so how
many Action potentials per unit of time
are these neurons firing and what's
being shown here is the multi-unit
activity as a difference between when
that sample was unpredictable minus
predictable so positive activity means
more activity during an unpredictable
sample I.E a violation of a prediction
or a putative prediction error signal
and all throughout the brain from V4 the
sensory area all the way to these higher
order frontal parietal regions we saw
without any exception that neurons were
much more excitable when they were
processing an unpredictable stimulus
compared to predictable stimulus and
also not surprisingly this started
already at the feed forward sweep of
activity such that these red bars here
indicate the start of significance so
sure enough area V4 was the first to
show significance so more spiking to the
unpredictable overpredictable and this
activity fed forward up the cortical
hierarchy
next we looked not only at the firing
rate of these neurons but also the local
field potential which is informative
about the local oscillatory activity
that's present so you can think of these
oscillations as massive waves of
activity that are synchronous across the
large population of neurons but of
course are produced through the
interplay between these recurrent
inhibitory bouts of activity and so
here's what we found We performed this
power spectral analysis again comparing
power in the unpredictable case versus
Power in the predictable case and we did
it we did a percent change metric very
simple percent change metric so again
what's shown here on the on the y-axis
is in positive more power to
unpredictable samples and in the
negative values more power to the
predictable samples now what we saw in
the gamma range so that's everywhere
above about 30 or 40 Hertz again in all
areas very strongly mirrored what we saw
in the spiking activity namely but there
was more of this high frequency and also
the classic low range frequency in the
gamma range so in both the low gamma and
high gamma ranges an enhancement of
power during the unpredictable cues and
that was also the case in the Theta band
and this makes somewhat sense from the
point of view of neurophysiology that
this Theta frequency and this gamma
frequency they very often track one
another and do similar things in cortex
why exactly that is the case we actually
don't know uh uh what the what the
reason for that is but that's an
observation that we've seen in many
other tasks but what we saw in between
the Theta and the gamma bands was this
other band at between 10 to about 20 or
slightly higher in frequency this
classic Alpha Beta band and this Alpha
Beta band
this Alpha Beta band uh acted in the
exact opposite way namely there was more
power to predictable samples closed
captioning not available
okay so next we had these laminar
electrodes so let's look at the the
difference between what these neurons
are doing when you record from the
so-called superficial layers of Cortex
versus the so-called deep layers of
Cortex so there so the superficial
layers are layers two three the Deep
layers are these layers five and six uh
these superficial layers they are the
layers that feed forward so remember
from that introductory slide that these
are the layers that were hypothesized
based on predictive coding Theory to
house the prediction error neurons
because according to Theory those
prediction error signals are sent in the
feed forward Direction so we we then
tested that in a second way which was to
test whether or not those enhanced
signals during unpredictable samples are
more present in layer 2 3 and that's
exactly what we found in V4 so when we
again take the spiking signal and
subtract unpredictable minus predictable
spiking we see that this the signal is
more enhanced in superficial layers of
V4 there was a trend towards that in PFC
as well but in V4 it was a significant
observation and furthermore when we now
look at the lfp gamma power this power
in the 40 to 90 Hertz band again we do
the the power change so these positive
signals mean there's an enhancement of
gamma power to the unpredictable signal
and again now in both V4 and PFC it's
The Superficial layers that are having
more of this unpredictable signal again
and that's consistent with the
theorized type of circuitry for for the
for these canonical circuits uh next we
I we we were interested in whether or
not these power changes were blankets
across the board that just overall
increased uh new activity and Gamma
activity independent of the exact sample
that was being shown or whether these
signals were actually specific to the
actual item that was being predicted
because remember in our task design
animals were for a large portion of time
predicting that there should be a car
stimulus or predicting an orange or
predicting the green stimulus so in that
particular task requirement it wouldn't
make sense if
um if task representations for all three
stimuli all went up to an unpredictable
stimuli that would be more consistent
with just an overall arousal signal but
what we were next interested in is
whether or not neurons that actually
were selected for the car if it was
those neurons in particular that had the
unpredictable signals
and what we found is that that was
indeed the case so we performed the same
analysis as before lfp gamma power
difference for unpredictable minus
predictable but now as a function of
whether or not those neurons preferred
the stimulus that was being predicted
and what we found is that the preference
actually modulated this gamma band
activity very strongly and so it was
this this unpredictable signal change
was more specific to neurons that
actually preferred that predicted
stimulus indicating that this prediction
was not acting as a blanket similar to
an arousal mechanism but was actually
reaching down at the level of the
representations that were specific to
the thing that needed to be predicted
and that that was even more the case in
the beta frequency range actually where
the neurons that didn't encode the
predicted stimulus they couldn't care
less whether or not that stimulus was uh
was was predictable it was really only
neurons that that carried information
about the stimulus that was being
predicted those were the neurons that
were were not enhancing but diminishing
their beta during an unpredictable
signal or set another way enhancing
their beta to a predicted signal change
so here's what we think is going on we
call we call this neurophysiological
implementation that we found of
predictive coding we call it predictive
routing to make a a semantic point but
also a a slightly more
neurophysiological and computational
argument that we don't actually find
strong evidence for this mismatch and
prediction signal at the level of
neurons but instead we think that this
prediction
um
circuit exists but uses these
oscillations in order to implement what
is predicted so here's how we think this
works so when a prediction matches a
stimulus as is being shown here when
you're predicting a and you get a
stimulus a then the a column the in
other words it doesn't have to be a
column but the the area of the brain or
the neurons that encode a are going to
become prepared to receive the stimulus
a by enhancing the power of this Alpha
Beta signal so this top-down data from
higher order areas we think prepares a
cortical circuit to receive a predicted
stimulus and It prepares that stimulus
by enhancing that's this up Arrow here
the alpha beta especially in the Deep
layers which can inhibit both the gamma
and the spiking signal in The
Superficial layers as a result
um so this top-down signal inhibits The
Superficial layers and as a result there
is decreased gamma and spiking and
decreased feed forward output in the
case of a predictable stimulus
the case of an unpredictable stimulus
well stimulus a just like before is
still going to be coming in but because
it's not predictable that column that
set of neurons that normally
represents a was not previously prepared
by an alpha beta signal and so the alpha
beta signal is relatively low in an
unpredictable context releasing the
inhibition that the Deep layers exert on
superficial layers and as a result
causing more gamma more spiking and more
feed forward output which in other words
what we are hypothesizing here is that
predictive coding and this error
computation comes about as a failure in
predictive inhibition and as a result of
the lack of these mechanisms being in
place during a unpredictable stimulus
there is an enhanced gamma output and
that's what we call a prediction error
that's what we interpret as a prediction
error
so here's the predictive routing model
one more time in a predictable stimulus
top-down inputs prepare the column to
receive a stimulus that preparation
leads to inhibition less feed forward
output in a unpredictable case those
mechanisms aren't in place as a result
more of the forward gamma output
so that's part one that's our cortical
neurophysiological hypothesis then that
we call predictive routing of how we
believe predictive coding is implemented
in the brain and next I want to turn to
a little bit more about how these
rhythms are actually produced in the
brain because one of the things that we
noticed from just placing our laminar
electrodes into cortex is that
independent of where we put our probe so
here's an example of prefrontal Cortex
activity we would see these high
frequency gamma waves and superficial
layers and slower frequency Alpha Beta
waves in these deep layers and you can
you can do this analysis very easily and
quickly to reveal this what we call
spectrol laminar pattern and what this
is is simply dividing each contact on
the probe dividing the power that you
observe at that contact by the maximum
by the contact with the maximum power
along the probe and what this does is it
normalizes power such that a value of
one is the layer that had the most power
at that particular frequency and so if
you look here on the x-axis this is
frequency so these red colors are
tracking which particular layer has more
power at that frequency so you see more
of this low and high gamma power in The
Superficial layer so that's above point
zero on the y-axis and more of this
Alpha Beta activity in the deeper layers
of the cortex
and so in a um in a large scale
um in a large scale
a survey of Cortex uh together with Bob
desimone's lab and uh Diego and so I did
this partially while I was at MIT when I
was a postdoc with Earl Miller and I
continued this now and at Vanderbilt so
this this was a really
cross-institutional study and involved
multiple labs and the reason that that
was important was that most Labs
specialize in being a prefrontal cortex
lab or a V4 lab or a lip lab Etc and
relatively few investigators had
actually done the necessary work to be
able to record with these laminar probes
in multiple areas simultaneously and so
therefore by coordinating and pooling
data from multiple experiments we were
able to record from a total of 14 areas
in the study that we have now now in
review and what we found was that
independent of the area we found the
spectral laminar pattern that was highly
concerned served across areas and so
here it is from 0 to 150 Hertz for area
V4 and the sensory cortex 7A in parietal
cortex prefrontal cortex in the front of
the brain everywhere we looked we found
that there was this enhanced gamma power
in these red lines here in superficial
layers and enhanced Alpha Beta power
into deeper layers
and what we what we then turn to next is
first of all well let's really confirm
um at a histological anatomical level
that it's really that that is really
these layers that it's is it layer one
is it Layer Two is it four that
expresses gamma
um and the same question for beta let's
really confirm that that is in fact the
case because it seemed like a very
prominent
um hypothesis and a very prominent
observation we wanted to to Really
confirm it
um so that's the first part of this uh
part two and then we're going to get
into
um which specific mechanism might
generate these oscillations and how does
that inform inform computational
modeling and so then this this was work
done in my lab at Vanderbilt led by a
very talented undergraduate student
actually Max lichtenfeld and so we
performed these histological
reconstructions here's the probe an
example probe where we perform these
tiny electrolytic lesions in particular
areas while we were recording here's the
overlay of the laminar boundaries so in
red here this is layer four and then of
course we had the electrophysiology so
we could look at the gamma power gamma
relative power the beta relative power
and the point at which they cross over
actually we determined was pretty
consistent in layer four and and of
course then we also mapped on the other
features of these things to the layers
and so here's here's what we found is
that the crossover the point at which
the gamma profile in red and the beta
profile and blue the point at which they
cross over at which their powers are
equal that tended to land in layer four
the peak gamma power tended to land in
layer two or three and the peak beta
power tended to land in layers five or
six
and so we mapped these distances between
these different electrophysiological
signatures or or
distinct profiles to the different
layers and we did this for several
different probes and for several
different animals until we were able to
get a very nice distribution here which
confirmed that indeed the gamma beta
crossover is consistent with being at
laminar position zero we called the
middle of layer four whereas this gamma
is in at the boundary between layer 2 3
and beta at the boundary between layer 5
and 6. and so here is our current uh toy
model of what we think is going on so we
think that
um that there's different inhibitory
neurons that are interacting with their
excitatory self-partners to generate
fast frequency gamma activity in The
Superficial layers and in turn that
there is enhance that there's another
type of interneuron that is generating
with slower time constants this Alpha
Beta rhythmic activity
so in order to examine this we again
turn to Anatomy we we again turn to this
question well then which exact
inhibitory neurons are most prominent
therefore from the layers that Express
these different frequencies
and in order to perform this work what
we did is we Quantified the laminar
expression of three distinct interneuron
subtypes that are known to account for
over 90 percent of the inhibitory
interneurons in the primate brain and
those inhibitory neuron subtypes are
parvalbumin positive Cal retin and Cal
bendin positive and importantly previous
computational modeling work had really
Sigma singled out the part of albumin
cell class as the critical class for
generating these gamma oscillations
because of their fast time constants and
strong synapses onto the cell bodies and
excitatory neurons
and so again we performed this
painstaking histological analysis where
um you you perform different stains
mounting cover slipping microscopy
semi-automated thresholding and cell
counting in order to be able to then
really have a quantitative view on which
layers have which cell types that are
most associated with with these
frequencies and so here's what this data
then looks like we have the gamma and
Alpha Beta electrophysiology here and
then at the same time we have the neural
the presence of different neuron types
the with the three inhibitory cell
classes here and and then we can perform
an analysis to determine which of these
cell classes is most strongly associated
with again
and here's what we found that in in both
the low gamma and the high gamma across
over uh 14 regions what we found quite
quite significantly was that the it was
really the part of albumin cell counts
shown here as a function of laminar
depth that we're giving us the best
explanation for the laminar profile of
the gamma rhythmic activity both when
you take a very wide band as well as
when you perform a low versus high gamma
split it comes out in both ways
so how can this inform computational
models of oscillations well here's what
we think is going on then we
collaborated with several people here on
this work including
um Sanchez Toto at all and uh and
computational modelers in Spain and what
we did was We performed an analysis
where we took uh different and different
interneurons with different types of
connectivity so these PV these
parvalbumin interneurons were modeled as
having strong
inhibitory connections to the pyramidal
cell class and strong self-inhibition
which has been important for gamma
oscillations previously and when you
hook them up in these particular ways
sure enough
um this and you measure the spectral
output of these neurons these P2 neurons
superficial pyramidal neurons sure
enough the express gamma and when you
put in different types of interneurons
with slower
time constants and different types of
connections to these deep layer neurons
sure enough they come out with more
Alpha Beta oscillations
so indeed
um they're they're this anatomical word
could produce even more in the future
even more accurate models of how these
interneurons work together and with
pyramidal cells across different layers
in order to express these oscillations
so this is really a work in progress and
the the one of the first steps towards
this and our ultimate aim is to really
pull together this Rich anatomical and
neurophysiological data together with
computational models to be able to
approximate the laminar structure of
Cortex to a better and better degree
so now so so the this next part here
I'll talk a little bit about a causal
test now of the predictive routing model
with um with propofol anesthesia so this
will be the last part of the talk here
um and so we were interested in
anesthesia I got interested in
anesthesia actually
um through my work with and contact with
Jake Donahue over here who was a very
talented MD PhD student at MIT at the
time
um and uh was was being co-mentored by
Emery Brown and uh Earl Miller who was
also my mentor and so we were we became
interested in this topic for the
following reason well first of all uh as
surprising as this may seem if you go
into uh to a Surgical Clinic and you're
administered an anesthetic such as
propofol well it turns out that the
anesthesiologists may not know exactly
the cortical mechanisms and the systems
level mechanisms for how that anesthetic
is being is actually working in the
brain and it's actually to this day
remains uh
more often than not the case that
there's actually actually no
intra-operative monitoring of brain
State it's it's far and few between the
anesthesiologists that are that are
actually doing that and so um Emery
Brown who's an anesthesiologist himself
is really pushing for more and more uh
adoption of tool of simple tools like
EEG and and spectral estimation methods
by uh by the clinic and so our work was
clinically motivated but it was also
motivated by the ability to test this
predictive routing model when
um when activity especially in
prefrontal cortex areas is relatively
silenced and so in these experiments we
administered propofol to again these
Reese's macaques and we recorded brain
activity there's these local field
potentials and spiking activity in the
awake state as well as in the
unconscious State and what we first
noticed is that in the unconscious State
there were these slow rhythmic bouts of
activity get about one Hertz one cycle
per second or slightly little little
faster a little slower than that those
are the slow frequencies and these slow
frequencies organize these massive bouts
of spiking which could sometimes be very
synchronous across cortex
um but that there were long periods of
Silence in between these ballots of
spiking and the unconscious state
and so propofol anesthesia we found is
accompanied by again these strong
increases in slow frequency activity
which create alternating on and off
periods for spiking
there's reduced spiking activity
throughout the network but the strongest
reductions are in prefrontal cortex and
sensory areas are relatively spared so
they're still quite reduced in their
excitability in the unconscious state
but prefrontal cortex is more inhibited
there is also we found reductions in
Cross areas synchrony and very
pronounced reductions in the alpha beta
band
and so as a result we thought we could
actually use this model this propofol
anesthetic model in order to test
certain aspects of predictive routing
because what what's going on here we
have lower order cortex that's
hypothesized to feed forward prediction
errors the higher order cortex and in
and in turn this these higher order
areas might feed back their predictions
but as a result of propofol these higher
order areas are profoundly impaired and
very reduced in their spiking activity
and the alpha beta rhythm is also the
synchrony between areas is is highly
reduced so what's going to happen in
this case well if you think from the
point of view of Simply everything is
going down then sensory areas in a
response to an unpredictable stimulus
should also just go down but if you
think from a predictive coating or a
predictive routing point of view the
function of these higher order areas is
to create feedback predictions that
inhibit activity so in the absence of
those feedback inhibition inhibitory
activities you might actually
hypothesize that there would be an
enhancement of the feed forward response
when that feed forward response is
characterized by an unpredictable
stimulus or prediction error and so we
saw we sought to test this out using the
simple sensory prediction Paradigm where
whoops we have a tone stimuli these tone
stimuli could either be repeated or
occasionally there could be an oddball
stimulus
and what we would expect is that there
would be enhanced feedback predictions
when stimuli were repeatable and
predicted and that the occasion of an
oddball would signal an enhanced gamma
feed forward signal
so we performed the auditory stimulation
task both in the awake state as well as
after there was an administration of
propofol leading to loss of
consciousness
and here's what we found in the local
state just as we found in the visual
cortex for an unpredictable visual
stimulus as as in the visual cortex so
in the sensory cortex my PhD student
Sophie Shang who performed this analysis
found an enhanced gamma so right at the
time of the local oddballs we have time
here on the x-axis frequency on the
y-axis and the spectrogram hot colors
mean more activity to an unpredictable
stimulus so there was an enhanced gamma
response to this unpredictable stimulus
decreased Alpha Beta to the
unpredictable stimulus or said another
way when the stimulus was predicted
there was more Alpha Beta And what
here's what happened in the anesthetized
state when we performed this exact same
contrast we lost the predictable Alpha
Beta signal and instead everything was
enhanced so there was a decrease in
frequency towards the low gamma rain so
ever so the the cortex just essentially
went into a constant ringing in the
gamma frequency range which uh to our
surprise was much stronger in power
compared to the gamma that we saw being
enhanced during
um during an unpredictable stimulus in
the awake state and the way we interpret
this is that in the absence of this uh
inhibitory predictive Alpha Beta signal
this gamma signal becomes uncontrolled
and enhances itself in in the local
anesthetized state here in area TPT is a
sensory area you should have mentioned
that
so now to conclude we propose predictive
routing so predictive routing is a
neurophysiologically inspired
implementation of predictive coding
which stresses the importance of these
Alpha Beta signals for implementing
predictions and inhibiting sensory areas
and areas of the brain that are
experiencing a predictable stimulus in
the absence of that you get an enhanced
food forward gamma output and this uh
this distinction between gamma and beta
across layers we found was ubiquitous
across cortex really suggesting that
something like this may in fact be a
truly economical circuit Motif that's
repeated across the brain
um and and these Alpha Beta rhythmic uh
predictive preparation or inhibition we
found we observed was lost in the
unconscious state with unconscious
unconsciousness being mediated by
propofol so by the way it's one of the
most often used anesthetics and that as
a result of this loss of predictive
predictive Alpha Beta there was an
enhanced gamma modulation to these
unpredictable inputs in other words the
sensory cortex was in a in a
disinhibited state and so with that I'd
like to thank my many collaborators and
the bosso's lab at Vanderbilt as well as
collaborators on the anatomy and
collaborators at MIT as well as my
financial support and lastly we just
started the lab about two years ago
we're still in recruiting stage so you
guys can check out my website
my ex Twitter feed and uh and email me
if interested in contributing to this
line of research research and so with
that I'll turn it over in case there are
any questions and thank you for your
attention
awesome thank you Andre I'll just ask
one quick question from the chat Dave
Douglas asks does propofol change the
activity of neuronal microtubules in any
interesting way
thanks Andre I'll just ask one question
from the chat Dave Douglas asks does
propofol change the activity of neuronal
microtubes in any interesting way
um I haven't looked into the microtube
kind of hypothesis that's one of the
hypotheses advocated for for many years
by people like Stuart hammerhoff and
um there has been some recent work done
by uh by George mashour I believe and so
you should go check out some of his
papers on on that topic but I haven't
looked into that and I am I remain
somewhat skeptical to the quantle
explanation uh for for Consciousness but
mostly because the mechanism doesn't
appear at first glance to be very
biologically
reasonable and uh and also that there's
not a lot of there's essentially not
very much data on it but that may change
um in in the coming years so
something to look out for
great one one other question more
generally how do you see experimental
work in the active inference ecosystem
and how do you see the synthesis of
theoretical and in principle work with
this kind of real wet lab and real
recordings on the neurons type analysis
that you're doing here
yeah so it's a great it's a great
question I think that what we need to be
doing as a community is having more
interactions between theorists and
experimentalists and so we wouldn't have
performed for example this experiment
here if we hadn't already been inspired
by uh biological and theoretical models
of predictive coding and uh and and of
active inference as well and so that's
really what we need and it is to make
not only
hypotheses that are turned into great
theoretical and computational
infrastructures and models but we also
need to be thinking about if we care
about the biology and we care about
trying to figure out the brain and we
should also be trying to map those
things onto neurobiology
and psychology right and so that that
involves them both considering this
neurobio the neurobiological elements
that may Implement and mediate active
inference in the brain as well as the
psychological and cognitive constructs
that we think are going to be
particularly sensitive to capture
certain elements of the of the theory
and so I remain very
um very welcoming to to that type of of
suggestion and uh and in fact there's
going to be a postdoc joining the
joining the lab soon Eli sinesh who has
been working at in very you know very
deeply in the active inference community
and so we'll have an opportunity there
to both work on Theory guided data
analysis but also perform more
theoretically guided experimental
designs that can go further into to into
the neurobiological implementation and
so this this was here what I've
presented
um really simply the first and small
somewhat step towards
um linking the neurobiological
implementation level with the
algorithmic and computational level of
predictive coding and active inference
and so the more interactions that we can
have between the communities the better
that that will that will be I think what
would be
um it would be somewhat of a shame is if
the active inference Community went way
too far into just pure Theory and that
and and delved into
increasingly increasing areas that were
divorced from from the biology so that's
of course one of the great
um critiques right of the of the deep
learning and more machine learning
purely machine learning driven
approaches uh is that they have been
um you know they took a little bit of
biological inspiration but then
um you know started using algorithms
like back prop that were very
biologically unrealistic
um and so of course active inference is
a is a response to that in certain ways
but in order to continue being that I
think that there needs to be indeed a
tight dialogue between
um experimentalists and and theorists
and so if you have any particular ideas
I'd be I'd be happy to hear them please
reach out to me
um by email or
um or through through X which you can
find here
on the slide
that's that's really cool that's awesome
you're gonna be working with Eli and one
final question this is from Alexandra
is it possible to detect the
contribution of glia to the neural
firing rate of the field potentials
that is a question that I have not
considered yet
so we normally do not consider glia to
be
um uh active in the network but of
course
um that that is likely to be an
oversimplification we know that they can
have interactions with neurons we know
that they can also have different levels
of excitability
um and of course that's how they can
regulate neurons metabolically
but as far as the contributions of glia
directly to the local field potential I
am not aware of how to uh how to
determine whether or not they make a
significant contribution
um the I actually haven't seen any any
work on that but thank you for the
question it's uh it's it's always good
to read
reconsider our core assumptions right
about the the types of the cell types
that are most important to to capture so
it's certainly something to think about
thank you
thank you all right thank you Andre
super cool work and good luck with
everything until next time
bye
-bye
all right
next up is going to be Keith Duggar who
has submitted a pre-recorded video the
pre-recorded video is called active
inference and the actor model
so I will bring that up right now
foreign
Keith's pre-recorded video on active
inference and the actor model
active entrance and the actor model
hello hello I'm Dr Keith thutter
platform CTO at x-ray an extended
reality AI company
and co-host of machine learning Street
Talk podcast
now
as we all work to build an ecosystem
based on active inference
software will obviously play a
foundational role
to make the most of the active inference
we'll need to use software engineering
paradigms that align with the principles
of active inference
and I think there is one tailor-made for
our needs
it's called the actor model
active inference in the actor model are
two deeply connected understandings of
the world
they provide foundational Frameworks for
dealing with the Dynamics of complex
systems
with a focus on autonomous agents that
interact in an Ecology of nested systems
I'd like to for some of their key
connections including the role of Agents
concurrency autonomy
uncertainty
and behavior adaptation
we will see that active inference in the
active model are both Paradigm shifts
away from a deterministic centralized
step-by-step thinking
to a decentralized network concurrent
perspective
of both computation and cognition
just a little bit of history about the
actor model
back in 1973 Carl Hewitt Peter bishop
and Richard Steiner were all working at
the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology AI lab to fundamentalize a
concept of concurrent computation that
included both structure as well as
adaptable algorithm execution
conventional Methods at the time lacked
robustness and secure mathematical
Foundation
there are collaborative effort
ultimately led to the creation of the
actor model
at the time it was viewed as
revolutionary due to its characteristics
of both increased error tolerance and
distributed computation abilities
throughout the 1980s and the 1990s
the actor model became the basis for
numerous research projects as well as
practical projects gaining popularity
for its flexibility and intuitive
approach to concurrent computation
it was primarily used in artificial
intelligence and multi-agent systems
sound familiar
new after-based languages like actor
salsan and erlang contributed to the
refinement of the model shaping it into
a more robust and flexible approach to
concurrent Computing and it remains
alive and well in computer science today
more recently the atro model is getting
renewed interests mainly due to the
growing need for distributed systems
cloud computing and Edge Computing
fueling the internet of things and web
3.0
these computer tasks are ideally suited
to take advantage of the aqua model's
architecture
which is designed exactly for modeling
concurrent handling of those large
volumes of data on the one hand
and fine-grained disparate autonomous
systems on the other hand
this application of the actor model has
had profound effects on major companies
that have utilize its principles to
handle big data problems such as Twitter
Facebook LinkedIn
so what does this have to do with active
influence I'm guessing you've already
heard some of the parallels in the intro
well let's start by looking at a few of
core principles of the actor model and
how they relate to the principles of
active inputs
let's start with the concept of
isolation
isolation means that an after in the
actual model does not share its state
with any other actor
it can only be affected by receiving a
message and it can only effect change in
the state of other actors by sending a
finite number of messages in response
from a software engineering point of
view this isolation principle limits
potential side effects of an operation
to a single actor thus improving the
system's overall predictability the
liability and most importantly if
embraced fully can actually simplify the
design
looking at the diagram we've seen
ecosystem of actors sending messages to
a particular actor which in turn sends
back messages to other actors
where is active inference well
let's recast receiving and sending
messages to a perception action cycle
and denote external
internal
sensory
and active States
and we now clearly have the necessary
Foundation of activation active
inference
a markup blanket
the actors of the actor model map
directly to the Agents of active
inference
in addition the finiteness the fact that
an actor can only send a finite number
of messages in response is also an
important share of property
because active influence models reality
it necessarily respects the resource
constraints of real systems and this is
nicely bathed into the foundation of the
OCTA model
let's look at another core principle
asynchronous message passing
communication between actors is
asynchronous
this means an actor doesn't wait for a
response after sending a message it
continues working it continues living as
it were
this is critical as it decouples the
actors leading to A system that can
continue functioning living and making
progress
even when parts of the system are slow
or even temporarily unavailable
Professor friston has said that the free
energy principle is the ultimate
existential question
if things exist what must they do
well the actor model claims they must
not wait on others
of course an actor can choose to wait on
others
but it must not be forced to do so
in the model it must be free to choose
this leads us to another critical
principle that both models share
autonomy
the free energy principle is a model of
physical reality
and our reality is after all concurrent
all throughout Infinite Space Systems
are evolving simultaneously according to
their local Dynamics
and therefore
this is reflected at the heart of the
free energy principle
of course
a model of computation need not
constrain itself to physics but he would
at all were seeking to develop a model
that did model the reality of
distributed concurrent systems and
luckily for us the actor model Embraces
both concurrency
a scene from The principle of isolation
and after autonomy
making it compatible with active
inference
next we come to nesting
the actor model allows for an actor to
not only receive and send a finite
number of messages to perceive and act
it also allows as an action the creation
of a finite number of new actors
these actors can either be nested within
the parent
say the parts of an animal cell or it
can be released into the environment as
independent actors from then on
this principled model fits nicely with
the beautiful concepts of multi-scale
nesting and active inference
this allows for actors to contain
ecosystems of actors both all the way
down and all the way up
lastly I want to cover two more active
model design principles
Behavior change and persistence
actors have the ability to change their
behavior in response to a message
this adaptability allows for the
construction of complex stateful
entities that can evolve over time
and indeed it allows for an entire
ecosystems
to evolve new emergent behaviors
when used for software engineering
decides a powerful tool for managing
complex Dynamic systems
active inference of course Embraces this
to the extreme
very essence of thingness is the ongoing
attempt to predict and add to an
environment and thereby continue to
exist to maintain one's mark on blanket
in a broiling sea of activity
along with this also comes the concept
of persistence
persistence allows actors to save their
state and to restore or modify it later
a feature that embodies principle memory
memory is a prerequisite for Learning
and adaptation
an agent's ability to predict
depends on its ability to remember past
experiences and thus minimize the
surprise associated with unexpectedness
the vital role of memory is also
emphasized
when we assume that agents have and
don't depriors either from experience or
inheritance contributing to their world
model
this world model both Dives their
current behavior and it is continuously
updated based on new experiences
contributing to their ongoing adaptation
and existence
okay great you say
there are clear and deep connections
between the actor model and active
influence
but
how does this help us in the active
influence community
well firstly in my opinion it is a
software engineering Paradigm we should
embrace
and if we do
there are of course after model
libraries and Frameworks that we can use
such as awka
Orleans thespian
tactics Proto actor and many more
which we can immediately use when
building active inference software
modules and applications
there are also libraries languages and
you know language features that align
very well with the actor model
principles such as zero and Q
Tokyo and rust erlang async await and C
sharp
Etc
but more important than the tools
available to us today
is the software design mindset that will
guide our creation of the active
influence software of tomorrow
the actor model provides a paradigm of
software design and Engineering that is
the most perfect match that we have for
active inference
this is evident
not only from the alignment of the core
principles we previously discussed
but also from the insights that active
inference in the actor model bring to
each other
for example consider what is now called
Hewitt's law
informally stated as everything is
everywhere
this law signifies the idea that in a
truly asynchronous distributed system
it can take an arbitrary amount of time
for a message to go from one place to
another
and any actor must be prepared for that
event
there are simply no such thing as
instantaneous in such a system
and no component can make an assumption
about the timing of another component's
actions
in fact one must act as if a message may
never arrive
this has important implications
it's just that it is impossible to
accurately and consistently determine
the state of the entire system
at any given time
because the information just may not
have even propagated across the system
and also attempts to implement Global
synchronization will inevitably
introduce bottlenecks and reduce
efficiency
Hughes law emphasizes the need for
systems to be designed in a way that
they can effectively handle these
unavoidable delays and uncertainties
highlighting the importance of robust
non-blocking communication mechanisms
and local decision-making abilities
in short a Hector model systems are by
Nature non-deterministic
does this sound familiar
what other Paradigm highlights
operation under uncertainty in the
autonomy to continue despite the
environment
Act of inference in the free energy
principle
active instruments reflects the reality
of an unpredictable World in which our
software systems operate
different outcomes may result from the
same initial conditions
due to the occurrence of events in a
random unpredictable order
this is the concept of surprise that we
all know well
where an agent updates its beliefs about
the world
when the sensory input it receives does
not match its predictions
both the actor model and active
inference acknowledge that the world is
unpredictable
even more than acknowledge it the models
accept this uncertainty as a given and
not something to be managed away
indeed as We Know
in the free energy principle the
uncertainty that we maintain in our
models is what gives us the flexibility
to adapt
perhaps this is just my personal line of
fancy what I imagine a future where
software modules Guided by active
inference
do away with hard-coded error handling
and swap in probabilistic learning
algorithms
that optimize themselves as the Aero
landscape evolves
modules that are robust and self-healing
distributed systems with no single
points of failure that focus on
predicted disaster avoidance rather than
reactive disaster recovery
looking towards the future we as a
community have the potential to push the
boundary
of both active inference Theory and
practical implementations of the active
model
by leveraging the strengths of these two
paradigms together we can create
software systems that are robust
adaptive and more aligned to the
physical world in which they actually
operate
imagine the future where software
components using active inference in the
actor model can anticipate potential
issues learn from past mistakes
and adapt in real time to environmental
changes
with this approach we can build systems
that are fundamentally more resilient
and more efficient
in my opinion this can bring a step
change in software reliability and
performance and scalability
and Heralds a new era of computing
weaving principles of biology and
cognition into the fabric of our
software systems bringing them closer to
life in the process
in conclusion
the coupling of active inference to the
actor model provides a powerful new lens
through which we can look at software
design and engineering
whether we leverage existing languages
and libraries aligned with active
inference
or invent new ones we are standing on
the break of of an exciting Frontier
so let's seize the day
have a look at the actor model and its
relationship to active inference and
let's shape the future of intelligent
distributed computing
thank you for listening
awesome
great talk by Keith thank you Keith for
sending that in there were some comments
in the chat
so Keith potentially if you want to join
for a q a some future time
but really cool presentation all right
the next presentation is by Sanjeev
namjoshi and this presentation is going
to be called
developing next-gen active inference
tools broadening accessibility
educational resources and the software
ecosystem
I'm going to start this talk
right now
hello everyone and thank you for being
here my name is Sanjeev namjoshi I'm
just going to restart it machine
learning engineer working at the AI
Services firm just because it's a little
quiet
all right restarting the talk
hello everyone and thank you for being
here my name is Sanjeev namjoshi and I'm
a machine learning engineer working at
the AI Services firm Kung Fu AI where I
primarily focus on computer vision
projects
today I'm going to be talking to you
about my progress toward providing
greater accessibility visibility and
knowledge of active inference and the
free energy principle
I'm excited to be presenting this
material at the Active inference
Symposium this year because the idea of
an enacted ecosystem of shared
intelligence perfectly captures the
philosophy that underlies the projects
I'm currently engaged with
I've spent the last seven months on
sabbatical for my job to work
exclusively on an active inference
textbook and related tools presenting
chapter presentations code reviews and
receiving feedback weekly at the Active
inference Institute
The Institute has provided a space where
interdisciplinary research can flourish
as the connections and influences of
active inference spread to other fields
it is consistently fostered the spirit
of collaboration and shared intelligence
that I wish to embody in my own work as
part of this ecosystem
I intend to continue closely working
with the Institute to provide materials
that will bring active inference to a
much wider readership
I originally chose this project when I
saw the great potential in the active
inference field and couldn't help but
make a comparison to the state of deep
learning in 2006 when neural networks or
one of just many possible models rather
than the dominant choice in Academia and
an industry
this of course all changed in 2006 when
Hinton and his colleagues released the
Deep belief Network paper which is
generally understood as a start of deep
learning as we understand it today
after some Hardware Innovations and the
release of the well-known imagenet
Library we started to see coverage and
successive AI in the news as well as in
academic research
but in 2012 deep learning truly provided
its value with alexnet and for the first
time deep learning achieved better than
human performance on image detection
tasks
start What followed was a proliferation
of deep learning all across industry and
research I've added in some well-known
Milestones just to highlight the
explosion of progress in deep learning
in the last decade though there is so
much more here that we could discuss
so what about the state of active
inference as a field from my perspective
active inference lies in the same
position as deep learning in 2006
influential and on the brink of
exploding in popularity
this paper which is from contributors at
the Active inference Institute shows the
current growth of Publications in The
Institute and its community in active
inference
in the last three years the active
inference field has seen a number of
important milestones
here I show just a few that broaden the
scope and attention to the field
we have the first International workshop
on active inference in 2020
we had the first active inference
Symposium and the founding of the active
inference Institute then called the
active inference lab
we had the release of the par at all
2022 textbook and the pi mdp python
package
and I see myself now as perfectly poised
to bring active inference to Greater
visibility and attention this is in part
because of the current academic interest
and deep reinforcement learning and
generative modeling
working alongside the institution and
other organizations my aim here is to
provide some of the fundamental
materials to capture the attention and
notice of machine learning researchers
and students to bridge this Gap to bring
active inference into its Renaissance
to this end I've been working for the
past seven months on sabbatical to
finish work on a comprehensive textbook
the aim of the textbook is to provide
the tools to bring active inference to a
wider audience primarily those in
machine learning research and applied
Fields such as Robotics and to decrease
the challenge in learning the material
largely by separating it from much of
the Neuroscience background that is
usually a prerequisite
this decrease in prerequisites means
Labs will have to spend less time
helping students becoming acquainted
with the field and researchers outside
of Neuroscience will find this book an
accessible entry point that uses
terminology familiar to machine learning
rather than Neuroscience fmri image
analysis
all derivations are in one place
currently in the field many derivations
are spread across different papers even
behavioral papers instead of just
technical ones and it's hard to know
where to look if you want to understand
a particular equation or concept
part of the success of deep learning in
the last decade has come directly from
focusing on narrow improvements to
specific aspects of the modeling
there are many open questions and areas
of research such as how to prune policy
trees exploring second order
optimization rules for state and
parameter updates and scaling active
inference
The increased accessibility for
researchers would also lead to many new
industry applications such as autonomous
vehicles robotics video game design and
AI
the textbook would also put a spotlight
on Bayesian mechanics and invite
contributors and contributions from
researchers as an exciting nascent field
grows and develops
part 4 is largely a literature review
and can be very helpful to those writing
about active inference from Fields such
as philosophy psychology sociology and
many others
and the historical context sections that
are part of this book provide a lot of
that context as active inference is
built upon Decades of research in
Neuroscience psychology and many other
fields and also draws upon current work
in many fields that have emerged in the
last 25 to 30 years
finally latex reproducibility may offer
interesting ways to rearrange the book
and integrate it with the code for an
online only experience
now I'd like to share with you some of
the progress of my textbook in the
general structure
the textbook is divided into four parts
the first part introduces fundamental
concepts to set the stage
in particular I have focused here on
presenting well-known statistical ideas
from the perspective of an agent
modeling its environment who States it
must infer from an observed noisy signal
the second part focuses on continuous
and discrete State space formulations of
active inference where the algorithm of
focus for the continuous State space
formulation is active generalized
filtering
part 3 which I'll begin writing in a
couple of months focuses on a sketch of
Bayesian mechanics and the required
background designed with the knowledge
this field is still dynamically changing
and evolving
here I will focus on some of the
fundamental concepts and ideas as well
as code simulations to allow readers to
get a deeper and more intuitive
understanding of some of these
challenging ideas
finally part 4 is a systematic
literature review that covers all the
various applications and extensions to
active inference that have been
innovated in the last six to eight years
these applications include things like
robotics all the behavioral modeling and
neuropsychiatry and human and animal
behavior theory of mind and so on
the extensions talk about how
applications of active inference can be
used to talk about Dynamic systems more
generally and apply to things like
ecosystems and to economies and other
types of things like governance and so
on
as of this week the rough drafts of part
one and two are complete and 10 chapters
have been presented to the active
inference Institute
in support of this textbook are four
separate tools that I will discuss over
the next few slides
but before I do that I would like to
First highlight some special aspects and
features of my approach to this textbook
the major focus is on writing this book
for a machine learning audience or
students learning in this and adjacent
areas Neuroscience is out of scope for
this book
many of the recommended and even
optional prerequisites that are shown
here are typically known by
undergraduate students in science and
engineering and certainly by graduate
students in these fields
nonetheless the book is written to be
readable by those that desire to focus
on everything that is the math the code
the concepts those that just want to
focus on the math but are not interested
in implementation
and even those that may skim over the
math and just try to understand the
ideas intuitively
one thing that's very important to me in
trying to express these ideas clearly is
by spending a lot of time working on
typesetting and style which is very
important to successful learning so I've
spent a lot of time attempting to make
my work clear and readable
to this end I have margins which collect
specific key terms for references later
which you can see in some of these
figures that are shown here
and these terms will eventually
correspond to the ontology project
ongoing at the Active inference
Institute
margins also provide further explanation
to accompany the text and this will be
useful to readers who want more detail
and explanation
there's a large focus on building an
intuitive understanding of the concepts
for example importantly all algorithms
are explained from scratch and this book
we typically start with a description of
the agent environment modeling problem
we then start the book with a univariate
case extend the multivariate case then
we introduce variational inference we
add Dynamics generalize coordinates
where applicable hierarchical models
action and also learning and other
modifications we might add to our models
we have a very big focus on figures
clearly Walking The Reader through the
text and giving detailed visualizations
of important Concepts
and in terms of how the textbook is set
up the early part of the book focuses on
basic concepts such as hidden State
estimation that is estimating the
conditional distribution of a latent
variable given some observed data
the aim here is to explain the modeling
Paradigm in the context of an agent
attempting to infer the states of the
environment that is the interaction
between a generative model and a
generative process a perspective that
differs from the Bayesian inference
style that is normally taught
um in universities and and many
introductory textbooks
typically introductory textbooks on
Bayesian inference focus on parameter
estimation or learning and part one
introduces the expectation maximization
algorithm as a way to explain the
connection and separation between hidden
State inference on the one hand and
parameter learning on the other
additionally a large Focus has been
placed on variational inference which is
explained in detail
and the book features a catalog of all
the different forms of variational free
energy and expected free energy in the
literature and how they can all be
derived from one another
the book also covers raw and Bollard
style predictive coding terms and ideas
such as key ideas such as prediction
error minimization
as well as clear and intuitive
explanations of fundamental concepts
such as surprisal
the textbook focuses heavily on building
intuition through derivation
and the general flow of most of the
chapters is to set up the problem that
needs to be solved which is defining an
interaction between the agent and the
environment showing the elements needed
to solve it which is usually random
variables and parameters that form a
joint distribution or generative model
replacing probability distributions with
their algebraic formulations and then
moving through the algebra to a final
analytic or gradient based equation
the reader should be able to recognize
most equations in the literature upon
reading this book
I'm also making extensive usage of
Bayesian networks and other types and
styles of graphical models such as
Factor graphs will appear in part four
there are hundreds of custom figures
that have been created so far and the
figures are detailed to give the readers
a deep understanding of the different
types of content that is covered
throughout the books and also summarizes
much of the information and equations
that are pervasive throughout the active
inference literature
another important focus of the textbook
is that many of the models that are
presented are also shown in pseudocode
which should Aid the reader in
implementation
and finally each chapter is filled with
numerous what I call experiments and
these experiments correspond to the
Jupiter notebook and try to show the
application of a concept in a simulated
environment
so a lot of these experiments start out
by generating data so we have some kind
of generative process and then we have
that data passed to a generative model
or the agent which then attempts to
either perceive and learn from that data
and even act on it
and the example that's shown on the
right margin here this is just a
perception problem on a continuous grid
um which has been divided into pieces
for the purpose of the simulation but it
represents a continuous State space and
the agent in the bottom left corner
shown as a mouse as a prior belief about
where some reward food is and its
environment but it then needs to use
um
perceived from sensory data that it
observes the true location of that
reward or food which is obscured or
occluded in some way by the Mist that's
shown in that figure
so these types of experiments give the
reader a better sense of how to apply
these statistical ideas to a real world
situation so we can understand how it
might apply to some kind of autonomous
agent
next I'd like to cover and shift my
attention toward Jupiter notebooks and
videos
and like to note that upon publication
of the textbook these Jupiter notebooks
will be released on GitHub and should be
fully reproducible using Docker and
other version handling tools
one of the big emphasis is on the
Jupiter notebooks is it has to be direct
correspondence between the equations and
explanations in the code and in the text
this will build a direct understanding
and show applications of the concepts
explained
notebooks are filled with simulations
and visualizations
many that appear in the main text
and in addition to that I have also over
the last seven months been presenting
chapter presentations to the active
inference Institute so far a draft
version of 10 of the 10 chapter first 10
chapters of the book have been recorded
at the Active inference Institute and
these are just some sample slides that I
prepared that try to explain these
Concepts in great detail
in the final stages of writing this
textbook video lectures will be
re-recorded and released alongside the
book
I also plan to create detailed code
walkthroughs videos that walk through
the different examples in the Jupiter
notebooks
now I'd like to talk about a few planned
future resources I'd like to work on
after the book is complete or toward the
final stages of the book to have further
support and Educational Tools
some of these planned future resources
include
a software suite in Python to enable an
alternative learning approach for those
who do not wish to learn about the
algorithms from scratch
and this will expand the possible
landscape of Engagement
as Pi mdp already exists I will not be
working on a discrete State space python
package but I'd like to fill the space
for things like active generalized
filtering and also just just an
availability of different types of
simulations of Bayesian mechanics as
it's currently defined today or at least
the different versions and varieties of
some of those key Concepts
I'm also very much interested in
Interactive Learning and my aim would be
to have these preset simulations
Concepts that are explained in text with
various simulations interspersed in the
form of plots and demos and other
visualizations
and the idea would be that the user
could manipulate sliders and knobs to
tweak various parameters that would help
aid in learning as they get a feel for
how these systems behave especially ones
most of these systems we talk about are
dynamics so seeing how they change over
time
foreign the active inference Institute
has made tremendous progress in the past
couple of years to provide a
collaborative environment of res for
researchers and for students of active
inference
I hope to be part of this ecosystem as I
continue to support the spirit of
accessibility and collaboration
and I'm excited to continue to
contribute to this ecosystem of shared
intelligence and look forward to what we
can build together
I would like to thank the active
inference Institute for hosting my
presentations code reviews and feedback
sessions and inviting me to present the
Symposium and also thank my employer
Kung Fu AI for letting me take time off
to write for the past seven months
please feel free to contact me at any
time email is the easiest way but I'm
also available on the active inference
Institute Discord
if you'd like access to the textbook and
related materials please send an email
requesting access and I can get you set
up
and that's all I have for today thank
you very much
awesome all right thank you Sanjeev
greetings
welcome
hi Daniel thank you
yes well
we're really looking forward to your
presentation you can share your slides
and go for it
great
can you see it uh Yep looks great thank
you
all right good so thank you so much for
for having me I'm really happy to
present this paper today and
particularly because it's the very first
time that I present this work so I'm
really looking forward to
um any um feedback
um and any reactions um to these work
okay so um the aim of this paper was to
apply the free energy principle to
analyze the interdependent Dynamics
between living systems on the one hand
and non-living planetary processes
and this hopefully would we hope allow
us to gain some insights into the future
states of Gaia and by Gaia we're going
to mean the Earth and formulate some
predictions and devise potential
interventions to alleviate future
dysfunction on the planet
okay so then um line up for the
presentation is I'm first gonna go over
in brief
um the theory uh the concept of uh Gaia
so known as the guy hypothesis
then I'm gonna go into just giving some
Essentials on the financial principle
which um I'm assuming that um it's not
really necessary but uh just for the
sake of the flow of what I'm my argument
then I'm just gonna present some things
on the free entry principle and
specifically on self-organizing
interacting systems
and then I'm going to apply the free
energy principle to the guy hypothesis
in a sort of like comparison analysis is
in like how do they if at all complement
each other for epistemic gain
and then
um I'm going to after uh having done
that this should be
um should allow us to inform or to gain
some insights as per the human behavior
in relation to Gaia or the planet Earth
okay so let's see how it goes so first I
want to introduce the notion of
biophilia which plays a fundamental role
in this work so biophilia
came first
um or came more prominently in this
particular book here and it's quite
interesting
um the idea is that the relation of
humanity to the rest of the natural
world is essentially one of dependence
and this is very much already in the
literature free energy principle
um but more than that there is this uh
view of the necessity of a continued
survival and flourishing that is utterly
contingent upon the state and
functioning of the environment so we're
talking about things like very
utilitarian things like survival
flourishing mental health right so
individuals interact with the
environment so to achieve that
but then on top of that we wanted to add
another conceptual layer which is or
concerns how humans possess an innate
cognitive disposition towards nature
which is known and developed in in this
particular other field of work as
biophilia
and this is the idea of a natural
psychological disposition of humans to
seek out and connect with other living
organisms and the natural environments
so this kind of like the idea that is
encapsulated in the whole framework and
Theory under biophilia
so then
um this seems to if that's the case of
as things are described by biophilia
then that seems to
um to bring us to a dilemma on the one
hand we have these natural tendency so
to speak of humans to engage with the
natural world
in a very uh positive and constructive
way and on the other hand we see the
lack of action to protect the Earth and
here we have in mind particularly the
case of the climate crisis so in the
presentation I'm gonna make my way
slowly towards getting to that and um to
better understand the Dilemma
okay so let's go uh in brief over the
Gaia hypothesis so this is a a concept
that comes more prominently in James
lovelock's book Gaia a new look at life
on earth and the idea there is that 3.8
billion years that life has persisted on
Earth and conditions have remained
remarkably constant and unfavorable
across a huge range of parameters
the guy hypothesis is that this
consistency or constancy
to be is is a natural product of
evolution
in a modification however of the
canonical Darwinism uh the guy
hypothesis somewhat modifies canonical
Darwinism how well by thinking that
rather than evolution of the individual
organisms on an inert environment
what divorce is the whole earth system
with its living and non-living parts
existing as a tight-coupled entity so
this is the kind of like
so to speak refreshing or new um way of
thinking that somewhat reformulated a
little bit of Darwinism right it's not
the emphasis is not how one's individual
organism evolves or species evolves but
the whole earth as a system so that's
quite interesting because
for example
um the the view that the combined
genetic wealth of information of the
whole system becomes much more prominent
here than the darwinistic kind of view
and this acquires characteristics there
are conductive to its continued
existence and in turn affect changes on
the environment
so then seen as a whole organism or as a
whole system one can look at Gaia or the
Earth as a complex system which appears
to have the goal of regulating the
climate and the chemistry at a
comfortable state of life
and these views and these ideas have
come to gain a more visual expression in
2001 with the Amsterdam decoration on
Earth system science precisely endorsing
this view on the planet Earth as a whole
system
so then the guy hypothesis is a complex
system in in in various ways because it
changes adaptive in an Adaptive and
non-nonlinear way it also displays
dynamical image emergent and sudden
tipping behavior
and when bifurcation points are reached
the new attractive states form new
attractive states are formed
and this means that it also
self-organizes and there is
interdependence between the processes of
the system
and finally the guy hypothesis seems to
be quite interesting and extraordinary
in the sense that it brings together so
many different fields such as ecology
climate science cybernetics complex
systems theory chaos mathematics and
philosophy of mine and that's just a few
all right so
then
um the idea is of the guy hypothesis is
that we could look at the planet from
orbit or as it is known the all review
effect and the guy hypothesis offers
this glimpse of fundamentally different
way of thinking of the planet of
thinking that in fact dominated most
mostly by human history so it's a little
bit of like
um that um very inspiring clip by Carl
Sagan the pale blue dot
whereby the world is considered so
throughout the human history there's
typically a tendency for the world or
the planet to be considered from a
single living organism though rather
than an it
so that's that's the idea of the
overview if I can take taking this
overview effect look at the planet as
this whole living system rather than it
okay so then we can think about the guy
I apologies as like Newtonian physics or
even as the free energy principle the
guy hypothesis can be seen much more as
a framework or a method of Investigation
rather than a falsifiable empirical
claim
so in this sense this particular
Frameworks they are and should be judged
by their usefulness and not by their
purported correctness
where usefulness importantly usefulness
is to be determined by factors such as
parsimony coherence and consistency plus
its empirical and epistemic power to
explain phenomena produce new facts and
so on in a given context and at a given
time frame so that's the stance on that
we think that should be taken on the
Gaia hypothesis
all right so now having said a few hours
on the guy apologies now
um I'm gonna just prepare the stage by
saying a few words on the financial
principle which are given the topic of
uh this conference needs an introduction
but for these purposes I must mention
just a few things
so the free energy principle we take it
to be the case as well that it is a
methodology to understand
um over-served patterns of behavior uh
sorry observed patterns of behavior in
the natural world so then we apply the
free energy Principle as the tool in
methodology to analyze these
interdependent Dynamics between living
systems and planetary processes right
kind of like these goggles this
methodological technical scientific
goggles that you put on to gain insights
into the future states of Gaia or the
Earth such as to make future predictions
and wise potential interventions in this
particular case with the care of
alleviating future potential or present
actually dysfunction
okay so the free energy principle
um very much align aligns with um with
this uh Thinking by Ewing uh schwelinger
and the view that the second law of
Thermodynamics or under the second law
of Thermodynamics starts open systems
like us should tend to dissipation
however interestingly there are displays
of this super cool thing the negantropy
which are pockets of the universe where
order and bodily Integrity are
maintained in the face of the search
towards chaos or towards entropy or
towards this patient and this view of
the pockets of the universe is
incredibly interesting because this is
where we find the self-organizing
systems like us
and what is so peculiar that
distinguishes these self-organizing
living systems from non-living systems
is that they have the capacity of acting
upon and exchanging matter energy or
information with the environment in
order to seemingly idify the second law
and therefore or thereby avoid
participation and
chaos and entropy so that's
extraordinary
so then active inference
um becomes this very useful tool to tell
us or to explain elucidate how
um these systems seemingly defy the
second law how this they resist entropy
how the self-organizing systems combat
entropy through the interaction
maintaining their integrity via
homeostasis
so then they maintain this energetic
Integrity they utilize energy to stay
within a specific range of states that
is vital for their survival and
preserving their existence
and they also engage with these feedback
Cycles which are the feedback actions uh
like drinking when thirsty or moving
away from heat
um signify working accomplished by bound
energy contrasting with the free energy
the thermodynamics as I just mentioned
by assumingly challenging the law they
minimize entropy and Safeguard their
free energy
and finally they this behavior that we
observe in this self-organizing living
systems
um in striving to minimize free energy
um is or agrees with a certain principle
that we know which is the free energy
principle
okay so then
um as I said
um earlier and as we know but just just
uh to keep in mind then active in France
becomes a very useful tool to understand
and make predictions about these
coupling Dynamics taking place between
interacting systems
the living systems internal States in
both is both operation and fully closed
and thermodynamically open to the
external States creating this distinct
boundary which we usually mathematically
capture with Marco blankets
and then this interaction unfolds
through the military or active and
sensory States
then the key Point here to keep in mind
is that what we want to have for
adaptation and well-being is that there
is a balanced interaction between
sensory and active States and this is
because it is in within the interaction
between sensory and active states that
so to speak all of the important things
happen in order for the system to be
well adjusted attuned adapted to the
environment
so living systems avoid this dissipation
they want to remain alive they do
everything in their power they navigate
their environments in order to avoid
this dissipation which is also or can be
also said to minimize free energy and
they avoid their dissipation by doing
either one of the two things either by
changing the model or changing the World
by acting upon the world and this is
extremely crucial for the point that I
want to make later on
so now
um I want to apply the financial
principle to the guy hypothesis and see
how that comes together
in identifying and developing and why do
I want to do that I want to do that
because I've also already mentioned it
but I'm just gonna refresh it because I
want to identify and develop
interventions to rectify any potential
maladaptive responses namely actions
which are anti-tentical to maintaining
the Integrity of the system what we want
is to have healthy well-adjusted
adaptive systems
and human behavior particularly that
leads to the imbalance within the mark
of blanket States is or could be
considered sometimes maladaptive or
pathological and this will be the last
point that I'm going to make in the
presentation but for now
um I want to focus on how does the
French principle deal with the guy
hypothesis
as a self-organizing system like with or
just saying the guy omits the
requirements to be formalized as part of
an active inference system it exists in
a non-equilibrium equilibrium steady
state
which means that its processes and
states must persist over time within a
range of states that are far from
equilibrium that means resisting entropy
and the Gaia is also distinguishable
from its larger scale Cosmic environment
such as other planets and the rest of
the universe
it is also defined by the conditional
Independence that we were just talking
about between the internal and external
stage which influence each other only
vicariously
so then we can taking that into
consideration we can even see that some
of the people have already done this
kind of like line of reasoning they've
already run it through and they did that
my employing Marco blankets to analyze
the earth's climate System Dynamics
which is quite interesting what they did
was they looked at metabolic rates of
the biosphere and they represented them
as internal States and space weather as
external States
and then they looked at active States as
mirrors greenhouse effect shifts and
sensory States as echoed ocean driven
temperature changes
and then internal and external states
are the idea here is that they
indirectly influenced each other through
oceans delayed response
then earth's climate is interpreted as
anticipatory minimizing variational free
energy so we take these work and we want
to take it a step further
um agreeing with this work and building
upon this work or which shows the
climate change uh we wanted to look at
um the more broad understanding of Gaia
through the lenses of the free energy
principle so instead of focusing on
climate change which is very brilliantly
done by these researchers we wanted to
then scale it up and apply the free
energy principle to understand
um the Gaia so then one can think of the
internal States as the biosphere
geographical processes and the external
States as this everything that that is
beyond the system such as the outer
atmosphere celestial bodies and molten
core then we can think of sensory States
as the external environment in part such
as the earth rotation orbit Tides
affected by the Sun Moon planets plate
tectonics climate weather influenced by
solar radiation space weather
Etc and then we can think of the active
States as Earth's adaptability and
adjusting properties from external
influence such as gravitational force
authors orbits magnetic field interacts
with solar winds or emission of
detectable radiation influences distant
objects that's a few examples
so then I want to focus on the active
States
active States then through this lens
active States then embody its primary
mechanism for self-regulation
representing its efforts to remain
within the bounds required for ongoing
existence based on predictions about the
present and future states of the system
for for instance the current levels of
greenhouse and orbital effects soil PH
and the number of living organisms
reflect the predictive attempts of the
Gaia system to adapt to anticipate
anticipated effects of solar events
volcanic eruptions ocean salinity
changes and other
environmental factors in the future
so it is in this context that the role
of life itself assumes a Paramount
importance in the self-regulation of the
biosphere because the role of life
itself and particularly as we are going
to focus on
um next the human life has a particular
influence on all of these sort of
already natural Dynamics going on uh in
the guide
um this allows us before we move into
the human effects this allows us to make
one final point before we move there
which is to address
um a criticism that has been made in
this paper by vicenter haha on the mark
of blanket trick and
um what they um have identified is that
a purported weakness of the financial
principle
um what we say is that a weakness of the
financial principle that is identified
in this paper actually speaks in favor
of its application to the guy hypothesis
and let me just try to explain that
and colleagues they rightly point out
that markup linkage do not automatically
capture every relevant property of
biological systems relational properties
such as affordances and by affordance
system in what the environment offers
the animal what it provides or furnishes
either good or evil fall into this
practice so what they're saying is that
Marco blankets do not automatically
capture every relevant aspect of
biological system such as affordances
right
and we want to point out that
um however
affordances correspond to Gaia as one
wrong in the ladder of the nested Marco
blankets
within the system in question at every
level ranging up from say cells organs
animals ecosystems Soul systems the
whole Cosmos and how is it that we think
that this particular framework that we
bring here does have or solve or address
the notion of affordances
our solar system is one that affords a
living planet
so the affordance available is an
environment in an environment are not
determined solely by the physical
properties of the environment and now we
think that this is the the point that we
would like to address in haha's paper
is that the affordances are not
determined solely by the physical
properties of the environment but also
by the organism's goals abilities and
previous experiences
and in this case of the Sun so what is
meant here is that the sun is what has a
furnaces for or what the force anything
else to happen on the planet at whatever
each scale right the physical properties
of the Sun as well as the goals and
abilities of the organisms on Earth
shape the affordances that the sun
provides so it's a quite interesting way
of thinking that any importance is
whatsoever that we might think of that
we have as living systems they are
afforded by the Sun so that's that's the
idea
okay so
um now having gone through how the
financial principles somewhat um speaks
to
um and contributes to understanding the
Gaia hypotheses
um then we want to focus on how human
behavior has a profound effect on the
Dynamics already existing in the natural
world
okay
so according to the free energy
principle living beings have a natural
tendency to act upon their environment
to prevent the suspicion of their
integrity so that's what we do in order
to remain alive there are therefore two
ways for a thing like us to minimize
free energy and thereby maintain our own
Integrity upon evidence as we navigate
the world and gather and observe
evidence we have to to to options one is
to change the model the other one is to
change the world by acting upon it like
I just said before
so then why is this relevant well this
is relevant because there is uh the
possibility that
um that in ways in which living systems
and in this particular case human beings
interact and adapt to the world there is
a possibility that we see maladaptive
Behavior
and how would that be well if it is the
case that there is a rejection of the
information available so as to remove
the imperative for action or if it is
the case that possessing the information
available but we still remain or refrain
from taking action then there seems to
be if the free energy principle is
correct if the financial principle is to
be correct that systems living beings
tend to act upon the world in order to
remain alive
um and if it is the case that one
rejects that kind of information and
does not take action to remain alive
such as the information of the climate
crisis then we might be looking at
maladaptive Behavior so if the free
energy principle holds then the observed
contradictory behavior is a maladaptive
state or should be seen as a maladaptive
state that arises from an imbalance
within the mark of blankets
and what is how do we see this imbalance
within the Marco blanket we see it to
put it in very very simple terms we see
it as an insulation of internal states
that are not being
affected by the information available
outside of the system so um the the
influences or the interactions are
occurring between internal active and
sensory States and this is an imbalance
that results in an insulation or an
equal chamber effect in internal states
that are impermeable to the information
from or potentially existing in the
external states that demands action
so then some foot for Thought
um what what can we make of this the
free energy principle if we are to use
uh the financial principle to model the
Dynamics of the relationships between
humans and the environment then we think
that it is possible to see the current
lack of pro-environmental behavior as a
pathology of the human species that must
receive treatment we label this
condition as biophilia deficit
deficiency syndrome biophilic deficiency
syndrome and and we use we it is
important for us to focus on that to
learn to learn some constructed to
construct some validity
is useful to consider
um in this case other applications of
the free energy principle that may be
useful as an analogous case of pathology
mainly conducted in Psychiatry and
neurology and in here and very very very
short because we don't have time the
idea is to see it as a failure to assign
the right way or prediction to
prediction errors so then the free
energy principle
um from this point of view this is a
prosenius pathology because doing
nothing is a base optimal response in
the face of pathological attention to
various sources of evidence so evidence
is
um ignored
so concluding and and recapping
according to the financial principle
living systems possess a biological
encoded inclination to interact with the
environment in order to survive and
adapt to the environment and despite the
climate change being a pressing issue
and the information being available the
evidence being available proactive
measures to reverse its effects are not
giving the priority they deserve
um these State of Affairs seems to show
very clearly a Divergence from a natural
inclination that we call biophilia or
that it's existing in religious Torres
biophilia this discrepancy between the
expected and The observed actions can be
understood in the framework of the free
energy principle or so we think we think
as an illness it implies that systems
including human societies may form
erroneous inferences that prevent them
from effectively addressing the problem
at hand
now thinking about future directions and
this is my last slide
um current ecological imbalances could
be thought of as a stuck State as as
that require an active disturbance to
bring about some change if not a stuck
state is a state that a system is at a
local minimum where the system is at and
won't get out of that state unless it is
Disturbed right so that's that's the
principle in in the complex systems
theory and we think that that's how
these um particular State should be
looked at that's for future research and
what we would be calling is we would be
calling for amounts to the kind of
homeostatic Awakening so the sort of
like getting out of this text state
would require some kind of like
homeostatic Awakening A deliberately
induced disruptive shift in the
trajectory reflecting a prioritization
of the planetary immune stasis over
infinite growth or staying in the same
place
and yeah this is my last slide thank you
so much I would like also to acknowledge
my co-author Casper Montgomery
um thank you so much for your attention
yes thank you
well a lot of ways to go I'll just ask
one question just in the years that
you've been in the game how do you see
the octave inference ecosystem and the
ways also that it's being applied to
ecosystems evolving like over what time
scales or in what ways does that really
presents itself to you
hello
I think there's um there's a lot of work
that needs to be done
um we try to do on this particular one
here to apply employ
um active inference to
um to the the planet or the Earth as the
living system precisely to bring out or
to overcome and
um so so one is to to to to to to look
at this problem of the climate prices as
what we think it is which is more of a
pathology if the Friendship principle
holds then it seems that there is a
maladaptive behavior of the collective
of the human species
um so I think that there's a lot of work
that can be done and that would very
much be useful in the climate crisis
um in general
um there is some other work that came
out more recently by Maxwell and
colleagues as well
um on the ecosystems which is really
really cool and I would also mention
that one and and I really hope that we
can we can pursue this this line of
research and employee active inference
in the French principle
um to this particular to this particular
case what what what really one of the
things that really attracts me to the
free energy principle is the capacity
that it has to uh to bring to the
Forefront
um uh certain laws of physics but also
the the living systems navigating and
interacting with their environments
which I find much more appealing that
any computational framework per se so
that's what what I I find that it's a
very useful conceptual toolkit that I
think that I would really like to see
more applied in the future for the
climate crisis on the Earth
great well thank you so much for
building on that line of work and for
sharing with us tonight so
thank you so much for having me until
next time see you
thank you bye
bye
all right
or gray talk by an S and now
welcome Aspen
how are you doing
hi Daniel I'm good
hanging out
um
yeah yeah yeah sounds good and uh yes
looking forward to your workshop on
sophisticated inference in pi mdp
so it can be um
up to 90 minutes or it's totally okay if
it's less and we can take a short break
but please
um take it away and just let me know
however I can help
great
thank you so much
um maybe I'll share my screen and start
so
regarding the structure of what we are
doing here
um I'm assuming that people who see this
later might want to try it Hands-On
along with the tutorial or something so
that's the structure I kept in mind and
so I'll go slow please bear with me
um so uh welcome all of you to this
session on sophisticated inference in
IMDb so here we are going to attempt to
model uh some sophisticated inference
simulations especially the one in the
original paper using the prime DP module
and how it is not part of time DP right
now but we are in the process of adding
sophisticated inference to the Pym DP
module and I'm going to mainly talk
about the code that I have developed
to kind of add that functionality right
so I'm Ashwin Paul I am a finally a PhD
candidate uh at Monash University and
mostly I work with active inference
models and try to understand uh how to
use them uh as an explainable uh model
too
basically understand emergence of
intelligent Behavior right so let's dive
into the material uh
that I do it so to give an intro of free
energy principle I'm sure all of you
right now have an understanding of what
it is but the central idea is that an
agent is always trying to minimize uh
the entropy of its observations right so
if an observation is having really low
probability uh in in your mind and and
that happens then you are probably
surprised and vice versa right so and uh
the entropy here is defined
as the information theoretic entropy
where if you have a low probability then
automatically this is a high surprise or
a high intro pick observation
and as we all know active inference also
gives us a methodology to Define what we
call an agent environment Loop and this
lets us Define what is the agent that we
are looking at and what is the Behavior
Uh of the agent given the environment
around it and so on right so you're also
familiar with the idea of Marco blanket
and this is important because we always
has to remember I mean have to remember
the difference between the generative
process and the generative model which
is quite a
famous point of confusion in inactive
inference literature and for the people
who try to understand it in the
beginning right uh so the central
question is that how does an agent
minimize entropy because
how does an agent know which observation
is slow or high probabilistic right so
that is by maintaining a generative
model and uh the generative model will
tell you which is a high probabilistic
observation and which is a low
probabilistic observation so the idea is
that all the agent has access to is an
observation that is coming from a
generative process which the agent
cannot directly observe and uh an
intelligent agent will try to build up a
generative model in its mind which is a
model of the Hidden States and the
observation it has access to and it can
hope to kind of compute probabilities
using this generative model right but
there is a problem that in general it is
an intractable problem uh to kind of
marginalize the probability of
observations from the generative model
and that is why we have to Define an
upper bound on the surprise that the
agent is trying to minimize and there
comes the idea of free energy right so
this upper bound the agent is supposedly
minimizing is the free energy and that's
why it is the free energy principle and
here we have a new term called Capital
Qs which can be interpreted as the
belief that the agent is maintaining
about the hidden steps in its generated
model and this quantity is the free
energy and traditionally we see uh this
variational free energy being
interpreted as
uh in in mostly the machine learning way
where it is a balance between complexity
and accuracy of the model so when
minimizing the free energy the agent is
trying to come up with a single model
but at the same time an accurate model
because here it's a minus sign with
accuracy right it can also be
interpreted in the physics way where the
agent is always trying to minimize the
energy of the model but at the same time
maximizing the entropy of the model
which goes in conjunction with the
maximum entropy principle and so on from
the classic literature so given that
this idea of a generative model is so
important
um in in a software point of view uh
that's the first thing that you might
want to do right to define a generative
model for the agent
um
which is informed or not informed
depending upon uh the experiment that
you're trying to model So In classical
active inference usually decision making
is defined in terms of policies so for
example if you are an agent in this
environment so in the Mario game uh
Mario is the agent and everything else
is the environment and
Mario has
um three available actions
um run jump or stay in this environment
and the classic definition of policy is
that it is a sequence of actions in time
so if you have a time Horizon of capital
T then a policy is nothing but a series
of actions you might take so run run run
jump and so on in time so this is the
superscript is the action so here it is
Jump run and so on and the subscript is
the time and then
then what you can have is a policy space
which is a collection of many such
policies
ah smaller pi and what you essentially
do to take decisions in active
inferences uh compute uh not optimize
compute the expected free energy of uh
every policy in your policy space and
basically that can be interpreted as a
balance between risk and ambiguity
and
yeah so when you compute this expected
free energy what you're trying to do is
minimizing uh the risk uh that is how
different is your belief about the
observation uh from your prior
preferences Capital C so this is also
part of the generative model when you're
trying to model control and at the same
time you are trying to minimize the
ambiguity when you are choosing a policy
that has the minimum expected free
energy right but this formulation has a
problem that a policy space quickly
becomes intractable that there can be an
enormous number of small Pi's or
policies in your policy space and
sitting and Computing the expected free
energy for all such policies even for a
small time Horizon is not possible but
uh this is the classical structure that
has been implemented in Pym DP uh
nonetheless where we have different
modules in pi mdp that is meant to be uh
implementing different aspects of
behavior so for example uh for inference
or perception we have belief propagation
fixed Point iteration uh marginal
message passing and all that
implemented in the inference module in
the control module we have a different
methods to evaluate expected free energy
for policies one depending upon the
expected utility uh the other one
depending upon the
classic method that I just explained
then we have a module for learning so we
learn the parameters in the pom DP like
capital a capital B so likelihood
transition Dynamics and so on and then
we have
algorithms for implementing all this in
the algorithms module and then the most
powerful thing in pi mdp right now is
the Asian class where it is easy for you
to kind of Define the agent environment
Loop and
we are trying to build up uh so today
I'm going to talk about an Asian class
that implements sophisticated inference
um rather than the classical active
inference um that we just saw
um so
as I mentioned um how many valid
policies can be defined say for a Time
Horizon of 15 in classical active
experience right
um so the first policy of course uh is a
series of first action that is jump then
you can have the last Last Action
changed and and you already can see that
uh there can be n number of combinations
and for this simple case uh the policy
space is as big as 10 to the power 13
and in a stochastic problem setting uh
there is no way to kind of
come up with a small subset of this
policy space so that you can tackle this
problem of computational complexity
and yeah as I mentioned in a stochastic
problem setting it is an interactable
size policy space uh there comes the
idea of sophisticated inference where we
are thinking about taking this instance
in a different way right so rather than
thinking about sequence of actions in
time we can directly think of what to do
when we see something depending upon our
beliefs about the current state and
beliefs about the future right so if I
see myself in a current situation what
should I do and that's more like a
straightforward thinking of
um
how to take actions and here we expected
free energy the structure of the
expected free energy is the same but we
are not evaluating expected free energy
of uh policies but uh expected free
energy of uh observation action
combinations so if I see something and
if I do this what's the expected free
energy and that's what I'm trying to
minimize uh that's what I'm trying to uh
optimize uh in in this setting right so
here again we have the risk term where
we are trying to minimize the deviation
between the belief and the prior
preferences we also have the ambiguity
term uh and this together makes up the
expected free energy of uh this time
point at time T but we also have an
expectation about what's the expected
free energy in the next time step and
um to evaluate the expected free energy
of next time step you will have to again
compute this equation with OT plus two
and and for that you will have to again
compute this equation uh with OT plus
three and so on and this automatically
becomes a research because of the
recursive way this equation is defined
and it comes with its own problems where
there are clever ways to get around them
and that's we are going to discuss that
in the code today so given this
structure of sophisticated inference
here as I mentioned the research replace
the policy space that we saw for the
additional active inference we are used
so in this
Workshop what I'm focusing on is how to
kind of Define a generative model
and and given an environment so for
example this is the grid that is
stimulated uh simulated in the original
paper and we are going to talk about how
to build up a generative model for this
grid that can be used in the
sophisticated inference in in the pi mdp
module and
so basically what I'm trying to talk
about is that the environment will have
a step function that takes an action
from the agent in biomdb and the agent
will get an observation out of that
action and we are we'll talk about this
particular function agent dot step and
agent dot steps will step will take up
an observation and try to give come up
with an action for the next time step
right and this creates a loop and
um
cleverly designing this Loop will let
you see emergence of purposeful behavior
in the sophisticated imprint setting so
for example in this particular grid with
sufficient planning Horizon you will be
able to see that the agent is capable of
navigating in this grid and so on so
this is the example that I am going to
focus on in this laptop today
so
I want to excuse me
I want to right away jump in um to the
code
so we have
um
the pi mdp home which I am I'm hoping
you are familiar with so we have this
GitHub repository where we have the pi
mdp module and inside time DP module we
have several uh
parts for it so here we have the agent
in the original Prime DP module that
implements uh the so-called classical
active inference we have several
environments and we have helper
functions like learning in current
smacks and so on so this is the module
of time DP but in the parent folder we
also have examples where
there is tutorials about how to use the
agent class how to kind of deal with the
environments and so on so if you look at
the pull requests so we are right now
trying to merge sophisticated inference
into the original Prime DP module and
today I'm going to talk about the code
in this school request so if you are if
you want to try this uh Hands-On you
might want to go to this page where this
full request is there and
it has the same structure of time DB
it's basically designed using by NDP and
here what we have additionally is an
agent SI which is a sophisticated
Enterprise agent which does everything
and also planning and decision making in
the sophisticated inference way and in
the parent folder there is also an
example folder uh for sophisticated
inference demo and what I am going to do
today is to walk you through this
tutorial of sophisticated inference and
on the way I'm going to discuss
and at points uh where I reference
the helper codes I am going to go to
that code and try to explain what's
actually happening and how we complete
that age in the environment Loop where
we can see that purposeful Behavior
right so
yeah so that's the prime DP home then I
also talked about the pull request so
let's right away go into the jupyter
notebook so this is my local copy of
this repository so it's easier for me to
run it and show it in my personal
computer so this is the parent folder
with Pym DP and examples and in inside
examples I have a demo holder for
sophisticated inference and this is The
Notebook I'm talking about right so here
in this example what we are trying to do
is
um deal with this particular gridual
task from the original sophisticated
inference paper and make this agent or
enable this agent to navigate to this
red dot which is supposedly the gold
state in this particular task given our
prior preference like this right so this
prior preference is quite informative in
the sense that we write we can see that
this is the most preferred State the
white color and the surrounding states
are kind of less preferred but more
preferred than the far away ones right
so this is the grid World task that we
are trying to use
so the first cell is
importing all the necessary libraries
and some useful libraries like numpy and
matplotlib and the most important one is
prime DB so I'm I'm actually now calling
the local copy of my Prime DP with the
sophisticated inference implementation
not the original one which is not merged
yet and the first thing I want to talk
about is the environment itself right so
the environment dot step part where if I
get some action how does the environment
work and
for that inside this folder I have and I
have a file which is great environment
uh SI Dot py and this is basically an
environment class so don't worry about
how this environment is actually
implemented the only thing to worry
about is
um
this function that we are going to use
which is environment dot step so this
function will take an action into it and
depending upon the current state of the
environment it will calculate what is
the most probable next state given this
action from the agent so that's the idea
and then it will also calculate the
reward of some a negligible negative
value if it is not the goal State and if
it is the gold state
it will give a reward of 10 and that's
how the environment is designed and it
will update the current state to the new
state and basically what it will return
is a new state depending upon your
action
um the reward for that action and
whether it is an end of the episode and
so on so this implementation is the
standard open AI environment
implementation and this is the
environment.step function right so in
this grid
for example if I am right now in this
state and if I take an action up so I
have four available actions
um north south east and west so if I go
north then the environment dot step will
make sure that I am in the state that is
about the state and if I go east or west
then I'll stay here or South I'll stay
here so that's the idea and yeah and
there is an episode length limit that is
eight here that means that I am
restricting the
um
length of every episode to be eight
which is the ideal length of reaching
this gold state just to avoid confusion
so in this environment after eight
actions the environment will terminate
and if you have to kind of Reach This
rule state in the optimal time point so
that's the idea how the environment is
implemented
okay uh I hope that is clear and there
are many helpful functions in this
environment like
um
rendering the environment rendering a
pride preference Matrix in this
environment so if you design a
prioritical friends this environment can
show that in in a pictorial way how your
prior preferences that you will see in
the notebook below
so now it's time that we Define a
generative model for the sophisticated
inference agent right
um
before that
let's define the structure of the
generative model that we want the agent
to have in its mind
which is tailor made for this particular
environment right so here in this
particular grade World task we have 25
valid States
um starting from this state all this
black States in this path are valid
States so there are 25 valid States and
then there are four available actions
for the agent north south east and west
so this is part of our generative model
this is also in alignment with the
reality of the grid but this is about
what the agent it has in its mind right
and then the observation is just the
state space the agent is uh it the
problem is fully observed so there is no
ambiguity there then
we define basically the number of states
then we define basically the number of
states which is a list of your state
space number of factors which is now one
because you only have one heat and state
actor here then number of controls which
which is going to be four uh that's for
available actions and your observation
space like that so this is the structure
of your generative model and let's look
at the structure of the parameters now
inside a pomdb so the first one is the
likelihood function
which is often denoted by capital A and
here it is a function of how many
observation modalities I have and how
many state modalities I have right so if
I run this cell yeah I have to run the
parent cells
to make sure everything works
so I've rendered the environment
the structure of the generative model
and here I have the capital A Matrix
which has a structure 25 25 that means
that I have 25 States and 25 of surveys
and here because it's fully observable I
am initializing it as an identity Matrix
of size 25 so
that's my likelihood Matrix that I'm
initializing for this particular gradual
task then the second element is the
transition Matrix so there so please
note that I'm using all the existing
time DB functionalities to define a
random a matrix
and then using an identity Matrix uh on
top of that so yeah I'm not doing
anything new here it is the existing
time DP functionality then what I can do
now is Define uh the B Matrix which is
also called transition Matrix so the
transition Matrix encodes transitions
like where I'm going to end up in the
future if I start from a particular
State and take an action so that's the
idea where it depends upon the number of
states which is the hidden State
modality and number of controls so it
has the structure of State action state
where if I take an action from a
particular state where I'm going to end
up so that is also a future state right
so
I'm going to initialize it as the true
environment state so now this is part of
the environment that I've built it will
give out the b Matrix
um it might be worth it to look at the
structure of this B Matrix
so here um we have 25 25 4 so that means
that if I take an action from
a particular state where I'm going to
end up and we have the true transition
Dynamics for this particular grid by
Design so there is a function called get
ruby and that will give us the true B of
the system which can which the agent can
use okay so ideally we would want the
agent to learn this but for the purpose
of this demo we are assuming that the
agent already knows the structure
and then comes the prior preference
which is uh interesting here in the
sense that
it is defined as how closer you are to
the goal state so if you are at the gold
state then uh clearly that is the most
sought out State you prefer that the
most and how how do you prefer the
neighboring states right so that is
dependent upon the square root of the
distance or basically the distance from
that particular goal state
so you define a grid
which is 8 cross 8 the same size as this
particular gridual task and then we have
a method to kind of add values which is
the preference you have for every state
and if you render the particular C
Matrix you can see the structure which
is the same where this gold state is
more preferred and the surrounding
states less prepared and so on
so now we have the C Matrix also defined
in the classic Prime DP way
and then I initialize that c Matrix as
the C Matrix we evaluated in the
previous cell which is small C this
particular C Matrix okay and then lastly
for the generative model we have capital
D which is your prior over hidden States
and for that I'm using a uniform object
array so that means that I don't have a
prior of where I am starting so let me
run the pending cells
so here the D Matrix is a uniform
distribution over hidden steps I don't
know where I'm going to start the
simulations and form so this is the
basic structure of the generative model
and then we have the agent class which I
want to discuss separately
like the environment right so given
these environment parameters how would
you expect the agent class to work so
where is the agent class inside this
folder structure
inside the pi mdp module folder we have
an agent SI dot p y
which is basically a class again
and similar to the environment class
here also we have a step function where
this will take an observation in through
the function and also a flag whether or
not to learn the environment which which
is optional so if you disable it it will
it won't learn the generative model if
you enable it it will update the
parameters of the generative model and
what basically it does is it will return
an action which is to be taken at this
point of time and the environment can
basically use that action right so in
this file we have the agent class which
I will explain in detail
so I am basically importing that agent
class in this cell
and then we are going to try and
reproduce this behavioral result from
The Originals of State influence paper
okay and for that
so what we expect is that given this
prior preference structure there are
local Maximas in this prior performance
structure so if you start from this
particular point if you do not plan deep
enough what you will end up is in one of
these local Maximas where you don't see
that there is a highly preferred
observation say four steps down the line
so if you are in this particular State
what you will see is this local Maxima
and you will go and sit there because
the neighboring states are less
preferred and this state which is more
preferred is not accessible because of
the world or the wall structure so you
have to take a turn and pass through
less preferred States and you need deep
planning in order to enable the agent to
do that the agent should be able to kind
of simulate
um four time steps ahead in time to see
that there is this uh highly rewarding
observation coming to kind of do that
actions so that's the point that we are
trying to
um see in this particular demo so for uh
low planning depth it will basically get
stuck in one of the local Maximas but
with sufficient planning depth it will
navigate to the gold state so that's
what we are trying to see right so we
have different planning Horizons
and what we are basically doing is give
the agent a generative model
which we right now defined the a matrix
B Matrix C Matrix V Matrix then we have
the planning Horizon of capital N so
here I am um iterating over planning
depth so n will be 1 3 and 4 for the
loop then we have action Precision which
is often denoted by Alpha in active
interest literature so that determines
which action is to be taken so a highly
precise action procession means that it
will stick to the action with the lowest
um expected free energy but a lower
accent action Precision is kind of
probabilistic where it will also
consider other actions then we have a
planning Precision which is part of the
planning function we will discuss which
is often denoted in the literature as
gamma then we also have a search
threshold which is extremely important
for sophisticated inference because as
we saw sophisticated the inferences at
research
and research is bad in the sense that it
can have a lot of computations but you
have to Define a threshold to kind of
ignore many possibilities to make it
work and that's the idea that we will
also discuss okay
so Desktop review before we go to the
agent
um
class what we are trying to do is in a
loop we are going to call the agent dot
step and environment dot step in series
so the agent will see an observation it
will take an action
that action will go into the environment
the environment will give it back new
observations and this Loop continues and
we want to see over time how this Loop
evolves into a purposeful behavior and
and if the agent at all is capable for
that so before I reveal the results
let's discuss the agent class so in
order to give an action when an
observation is given the agent should
have the planning and so on right so
here is the agent the sophisticated
inference agent
there we are actually using the existing
time DB agent for some functionalities
so in Pym DP we already have a really
well written functions
um for perception
um and learning so the only thing we
want to kind of replace is how the agent
is doing planning and how the agent is
taking decisions uh over policies right
so here
here we are using that parent agent
class so
from time dp.agent we are importing that
agent class
which is sitting next to the SI agent
that we are discussing now
and
basically we are taking in
the generative model structure from the
main program for this class to work
which is a b c and d and all the
precisions and threshold parameter I
mentioned
then it is kind of
um normalizing the prior preference that
we mentioned in the main program so here
if I look at how C is
the structure of C is defined in terms
of numbers and the prior preference is
often interpreted or it should be a
probabilistic distribution for the
computations to work right so
um we are going to normalize it as a
probability distribution
rather than
um having uh having numbers that don't
add up to one so that's what's Happening
Here we are using softmax to do that
then what we are doing is we are
initializing
um the existing time DP agent with these
generative model parameters and what we
are intending to do is write a planning
function for a given planning Horizon
and a given
um threshold for three sets okay so
um there are three functions in this
stage in class
one is a helper functions for planning
which we will discuss now then there is
a planning function itself which is
going to do planning using research and
then because it is a recursive research
we are going to need a additional
function that implements that recursive
evaluation where we are going to call
this function called forward search
inside the function itself so we are
calling this function inside this
function so that is to calculate
expected free energy for the next step
and it will call it again for the next
step till we till our planning Horizon
so that's the idea of recursive looping
and finally it will return the expected
free energy for all actions uh given and
observations and then we just implement
the step function where it is written
sequentially what to do give an
announcement okay
so going back to the demo
here we have this first idea where you
get an observation and it gives out an
action so let's go to the agent.step
function and imagine what happens
so if it is uh time t equal to 0 or in
the beginning of the experiment uh what
it is ideally supposed to do in the
first place is in for that state using
its observation so what we are giving it
is an observation and using the modules
for inference it's going to come up with
a belief Qs which is an which is a
belief about States okay so self dot Qs
is the belief in inside the agent and
once it has a belief about where it is
right now it can Implement plan dot
research which is um do planning for
this particular belief of hidden state
right now and once it has done planning
it can take decision using the sample
action function in time DB and basically
return it uh return that action and if
it and for every other time steps the
sequence Remains the Same but it is also
learning about the structure if you
enable learning in in Eurasian class
so that's the step function but in order
to do planning what it does is it kind
of reorganizes the generative model
structure for any number of heat and
state modalities and any number of
observation modalities
so to discuss how melting works I would
like to talk about
um the new a matrices and V matrices it
it evaluates for implementing that
planning and
let's understand that
so let's go back to the original
um
hidden State factors so here we only
have one hidden State Factor
um so that's why it is d0 right and B1
does not exist because we only have one
hidden State Factor but imagine that if
I have two hidden State actors
with the same size maybe
um so here it it could be a location and
maybe something else inside the agent's
mind
and we should also have controls for
these two hidden State factors just like
um
so there should be control for every
hidden State Factor if you're familiar
with active inference
idea
and then maybe the observation space is
also directly observing these two date
and state factors
okay so this is a new generative model
structure with multiple hidden States
and multiple observation modalities and
right away you can see that the
dimensionalities of your parameters
change you have 25 observations coming
from
25 times 25 hidden States and if you
look at the structure of the first
observation modality it's the same but
what we want is a new Matrix where it's
going to be 25
with not two hidden States but just one
written State it's only a reorganization
of
um the generative model but
computations essentially Remains the
Same
so
that's what this helper function is
trying to do which will make things
easier for us when we have multiple
hidden state modalities so
um if you have multiple hidden state
modalities
we are going to compute how many total
states you have which is the
multiplication of number of written
States in each modality okay so if you
have 25 hidden States in one modality
and 25 hidden states in the other
modality you're going to have 625 total
number of scales and if you have four
actions each in each modalities then you
have total of 16 actions which is
nothing but the combination of these
four acts each in in in the modalities
So you you're going to have 4 times 4 16
actions if you have two modalities and
it's basically
um going to build a generative model
that is the same
um model parameters but just with the
different dimension structure so that
it's easier for us to calculate the
expected
so now we have a new a and new B
and a new belief which is nothing but
tensor products of existing parameters
and beliefs it's nothing but a new big
Matrix and nothing else okay it's not a
transfer it's not a change it's just a
transformation of structure and given
this a b and Q we are going to predict
what's going to happen in the future and
evaluate the expected energies for them
so
in order to do planning so that's the
second function what we are going to do
is first call the first function which
will do the melting for us and set up
the generative model in in good
Dimension cc to compute then we have the
expected free energy itself for all the
actions
and then we have the probability that
depends upon this expected free energy
for these actions so why is it just the
actions and not the observations because
here we are going to evaluate expected
free energy of actions
uh for the given observations right so
let me
um go back to the
slides and discuss this
pictorially to make things easier so
here we have the grid and we have the
fire Footprints and what we are trying
to implement is that if You observe some
observation at time T then you are going
to consider the consequences of your
actions given that observation because
you can predict what's going to happen
because in your generative model you
have the transition dynamics that will
tell you given this state if I take this
action where I'm going to end up right
so that's basically predicting what's
going to happen in the future and you're
right now considering the consequence of
um available actions in Your Arsenal and
then if you take an action then you can
predict what's going to happen in the
next time step as a new observation
right so you have a probability
distribution that tells you that say
this observation is the most likely uh
and the other observations are not
really likely uh then what you will do
is you do this again you consider the
consequence of doing your actions from
that particular observation and and this
goes on in your planning depth right so
this can be thought of as maybe you want
to go to the gym then you are going to
consider all the consequences what will
happen if I wear my shoes if I don't
wear my shoes uh if I go in my car if I
don't go in my car then you realize that
okay I have to wear my shoes then you
consider the consequence that
I am now ready to go to the gym and me
going to the gym will end up me being in
the gym so that's the idea like you
consider the consequence of where you
are right now and you can go as much as
you want right you can predict so in a
game of chess you might be in a
particular State you consider your
consequences you see the future you
consider consequences from that future
and you can go as deep as you want
um
depending upon your computational
abilities right so that's what you're
trying to implement in this agent class
where we are considering consequences
yeah
so
for every modality we are going to
consider the expected free energy for
actions
and
this will basically call the next
function which is forward search so
forward search is implementing the thing
that I just mentioned
um considering consequences and in
forward search what you are basically
doing is for every action so in line 149
I have a loop that goes over every
action
then I am going to consider the
posterior or the consequences of all
those actions I use my transition
probabilities to evaluate that
consequences
then I am going to predict the
observations because my prior
preferences are defined in terms of
observations I am going to predict my
observations and then evaluate the
expected free energy
which is the sum of risk and ambiguity
okay I hope that makes sense like here
you have considered the consider the
consequence
which is consequence of future which is
post or posterior
and you're basically evaluating how good
that posterior is depending upon your
expected rate and that becomes the
expected free energy for that particular
action and you do this for all the
actions
okay and why this is powerful it is
because you can go as deep as you want
so here in the next step you go to this
loot
where you will check if I am crossing my
deep planning or the depth of planning
and then you are doing basically the
same given that posterior what is the
consequence of the actions of that
particular posterior so here
for considering that we are again
calling um the parent function so the
same function forward search to consider
consequences of those combinations and
it will basically come back and add up
to your expected free energy so what
happens over this sequence is that you
consider some or all future consequences
and then all that values will
trickle up
your tree and your that sum of the
expected free energy will tell you which
action is good or which action is bad
which you can take
um in to kind of see your preferred
observations
so that's the idea of implementing
research and I will also talk about the
importance of uh this threshold here uh
which is which is which makes this
algorithm possible so without this
threshold this algorithm will not work I
will explicitly talk about why that is
the case and then
once you evaluate the expected free
energy for all available actions given
the present State you can basically
compute
um what you call the action distribution
that is how probable is my action or how
I should take my action
so that is and we also have this action
Precision parameter Alpha so if Alpha is
very high then it basically is a
highly skewed distribution where you
will always choose the action that
minimizes expected free energy if Alpha
is really is low then it's going to be a
more
um sparse or spread out distribution and
then you can use this action
distribution
to sample actions and so in in the Asian
environment Loop we just finished doing
planning and Computing that action
distribution then using that accent
distribution you can sample an action
from your policy space so let's look at
the policy space in this generative
model
so I'm switching back to the original
generative model with one hidden State
Factor
and
let's do planning
and maybe
um initialize this agent
I just want to initialize this agent to
see the policy space not randomly
so
I initialize this agent say for planning
depth of one and if I look at
agent Dot
policies
I can say that I have basically four
available actions uh which is not
Southeast and West and if I have an
action distribution uh it will tell me
how probable is to take that action so
if I look at
agent
to Pi so okay so this is not defined
because I have not done planning uh but
I can do planning and then it will be
defined
yeah so I implemented planning with
research and then now I have an action
distribution so for this particular
scenario I am going to take my third
action the most which is 0.99 basically
that's the probability which is
north south and east in this particular
region I just wanted to kind of
familiarize you with the matrices but we
are now going to see
um the agent environment Loop in action
and
yeah so now you can sample an action
from the sample action function and then
Implement learning which is using the
standard Pi mdp way where I will update
my transition Dynamics and likelihood
Dynamics depending upon what I see and
what's my belief and so on so my
emphasis is on the decision making part
so once you sample an action then that
action basically goes back to the
environment okay so now let us
implement this for a planning depth of
one and see how the agent behaves
so here if it is a planning depth of one
then that means that the agent is only
considering the consequence of one time
Step Ahead just seeing the immediate
future for doing planning right so I'm
giving the planning depth of one I'm
resetting the environment where the
agent is going to start from that
initial start state
and
and in the loop it's going to
um
get that observation
take that action uh give back an action
and we will look at the action
probabilities uh and also we will give
that action back to the environment get
back the observation and this Loop
continues till the episode is terminated
and I have set the episode length to be
eight just to see the outcome of a tax
so when we run this Loop these matrices
are nothing but the action distributions
of How likely each action is to be taken
and this is where the agent end up in
the last text okay so let's maybe kind
of also enable this a environment.render
that will show us where the agent is at
every time step
so initially the agent was at this
location and we have an action
distribution of this here so north south
east and west so the agent knows that it
should go north why because if I look at
the prior preference
um this state is more preferred than
this state right so the agent
successfully calculated the expected
free energy and inferred that okay I
should go to this state and not stay in
the state and because it has the
generative model of transitions
available it can infer that I should
take that action North to go to the
state
so that's good and the agent goes to
north and at this particular State the
agent infers that it should go to north
south east so it will take an action
East
uh and it will go here and at this point
of time uh I want your attention where
the action distribution is equally
probable for north and east why is that
because the agent is only looking at the
immediate future right so let's go back
to the
prior preference where the agent is
right now here
or is it here yeah it is right now here
in this particular State and if the
agent is considering immediate
consequences of just one action then
these two states are equally good for it
to be in the next step so there is no
distinction between these two states if
it is only looking at the immediate
future so that means that the expected
free energies will conclude that I
should go to North or east it doesn't
matter if I'm looking at just one time
Step Ahead okay that's the idea
and out of probability it is going here
it took the action East and from this
um
State when it's doing inference it's
inferring that this state is better and
basically it's end up ending up in this
local Maxima state
which is this particular state where the
neighboring states are less prepared and
this is wall and you can you can't go
there because it is forbidden for the
agent by structure so it's basically
going to sit there forever where it only
sees that local Maxima of priorities
and
let's look at what might happen if you
have higher planning depth so if I go to
the planning depth of 3
um then that means that the agent is
actually reaching the gold state at the
last time step but still in the third
time Point uh it had
two probabilistic actions not an East so
here from this particular State out of
probability it took the action North but
it cannot equally take the action East
and end up in this local Maxima so let's
run again and probably it will end up in
this local maximum okay and
only for the planning depth of 4 which
is sufficient enough uh which is
necessary for this particular grid
um the agent is fully sure of what to do
so at every time point it is fully sure
of what to do uh that it has to go north
then east north north east east and
south and reach this particular state so
only for time step
um or planning depth n equal to 4 it can
successfully navigate this grid
um it's 100 certainty so that's the idea
next implementation that I hope you got
so there's also this idea of action
Precision so here it's a high action
Precision that is why it is taking the
actions that is from the probability if
it is a low action Precision
um like one then
the good actions are more probable but
that doesn't mean that it will be taken
right here by luck it is taking the
right actions and reaching the state but
here probabilities are most passed but
you will also see like exploration
Behavior Uh in more number of Trials if
you control this action process so I set
it to a high value to make sure that the
agent reaches the goal
um for this particular problem but it's
worth playing and it's important
right
okay
um
yeah so for different planning
um depths like one three and four in
this problem this is the behavior that
you expect for lower planning depths
which is not sufficient the agent ends
up in local Maximus and
or local minimas of expected free energy
or local Maximas of fried blueprints but
with sufficient planning that it's able
to navigate and reach the goal
so that brings us to the last point in
this tutorial
where why is it important to have a
threshold
in
evaluating substituted inference so
by threshold what we mean is that we can
ignore future possibilities in two
levels right you can ignore
um not likely actions or not likely
observations in this research but if you
consider the consequences
of all actions and observation that
means that you'll have to consider four
consequences in the first place then you
will have to consider four times the
action states in the next time step
for the next time step then all of that
multiplied with the number of actions
and this research becomes intractable
until explode and it's even worse than
the classical active inference policy
space problem but by defining a
threshold of even a small value will
ignore possibilities
so where is that implemented
in the forward search algorithm
um we are considering actions uh with
only action probabilities greater than
the particular threshold here I am
defining it as 1 by 16. uh also in the
parent paper it's 1 by 16.
um the action probability
okay uh so if it is 0 then that means
that it will consider all the
consequences of future and that's
interactable so you can ignore actions
which is not probable and also ignore
states which is less likely or only
consider States
um that has probability greater than
this particular threshold value and that
significantly reduces the computational
complexity where you will only consider
combinations that are probably in in the
future uh tree and that lets you go
deeper in your planning Horizon
that's an important Point here and if
you compare
um
the time that takes for deeper plannings
uh for a search threshold of zero
uh so address search threshold of 0 0
means that you will consider all
consequences and
the more deep you plan
um the more time it takes and if you see
uh to consider only the first future or
the immediate future it takes 0.01
seconds
for considering three possibilities into
the future it takes three seconds and
for four it takes 300 seconds then you
can see that the computational time is
exponentially growing but if you have a
very small search threshold
um you have that computational time that
makes sense for implementation uh in in
real world right so here for n equal to
4 that is four time steps into the
future it's only taking 0.1 seconds and
that's okay it I can still do
simulations with this complexity but
there is no way I can talk about how
this is
um how less the computational
complexities it truly depends on uh the
nature of your prior preferences and
environment in action but this such
threshold actually works in in real life
and we just saw that in our simulations
right for n equal to 4 it took only like
0.3 seconds in our simulations but if
you set the search threshold as zero
um it already is 300 seconds for doing
full debt planning and if I set uh
planning depth of five then it will
basically Run Forever maybe again I I
would not be able to do symbols
so that's the idea of search threshold
um so actually that's it
I wanted to explain the
age and class
the environment class and the particular
demo and yeah maybe it's a good time for
questions if if anybody was listening uh
and I hope people
um get to play with this code
um and look at the tutorial and and
implement this and build generative
models like this so this particular
example is
how do you build a generative model for
this gridual task and see how the agent
is able to take meaningful actions but
here we gave it the true structure of
the environment in the B Matrix and a
matrix and so on but you can also play
around with
learning in in the sense that while
defining
the agent dot step you can add a flag
that says learning equal to true
and if you start with an uninformed a b
and so on you can experiment on how the
agent is learning that environment here
you can look at the B Matrix in the
beginning you can look at the B Matrix
after say 10 trials and see how the
learning is taking place here it doesn't
matter because the agent knows the
structure and it won't learn much but if
it starts from
unknown structure then there is scope of
learning also to be implemented and it's
already implemented because
we are using uh existing Pi mdp
functionalities uh for learning A and B
and it's already part of the step
function
so I hope
step function is clear
um which is the only thing you need to
know if you are trying to implement
sophisticated inference and just the
names of these matrices if you want to
probe them and look at them and yeah I
hope the session was useful so I thank
my collaborators and
Corner who maintains IMDb and also
Brendan who runs the prime DP Fellowship
which I was part of and that's where I
worked on implementing sophisticated
interns in my mdp and it will be part of
the original Pi mdp module soon and I
hope people can start using this module
to simulate so stated inference
experiments and this basically becomes
so maybe it's a good time to discuss
questions or clarifications on the code
or maybe it's a good time to take a
break yes
thank you that was awesome
well I have a few different questions
and I'll read a few
from the live chat so I'll first just go
to the live chat and then um
ask those and then ask some other
questions so Dave asks
how do you think about the neural
implementation of recursion brains don't
seem to implement computer hardware
style recursion deeper than a stock
depth of one aside from heavily
overlearned tasks we can confine
ourselves to asking about recursion for
the purposes of exploring temperately
deep State spaces searching forward in
time
so how do we how do we reconcile this
really beautiful and elegant and
computationally efficient
full depth research with the biological
basis of multi-scale planning
yeah
um so I'm not an expert in neural
computation but the answer to that would
be
um
basically you're doing only one
competition at a time right and your
have or all you have need is some memory
to store your beliefs and use those
beliefs to kind of do the same
computation again so
um we are not talking about uh neural I
mean this hardcore recursive
implementation we are only doing local
computations at a time and just because
of the structure of the generative model
and we and because we have memory
um this this can be done and and I don't
see why and brain can't do it even
though individual neurons might not be
able to do it the main brain has memory
the brain has the ability to store
memory and the ability to dream the
ability to simulate uh it knows the
consequences of actions and you do this
on a daily basis where
um you plan your future and decide what
to do right so on a single neuron level
I'm not really sure
of how to answer that question but I
don't really see why the brain can't do
it as an organism
cool
um okay to the code I guess I have a few
questions let's can we go back to the
maze
and of course if anyone else has
questions in the live chat just go for
it
um
so in in the Maze how how does the uh
the moves that are possible
how is that reflected what what stage is
it updated that what for example that it
initially knows that it can only go up
and then it can only go right or down
where is that reflected with the
updating of what what the like kind of
that relational aspect of affordances
what is even possible to do
and then how does it evaluate in a deep
tree search
when it does does it need to know what
things could or couldn't happen in the
future
um so if I understand the questions
correctly
um
there is import there is an important
distinction between the generative
process and the generative model right
so in the great world
um which is the generative process
um we have implemented all of that
manually where we have this transition
Dynamics
um that
already knows what will happen if you
take an action from a state so it's like
an environment that knows how to work
um so it's like a reality where there
are consequences of actions and it's
already there but this information is
available to the agent uh to be part of
its generative model and in the
generative model what it basically does
is use that transition Dynamics which is
given or learned to simulate what might
happen in the future okay so once I have
that transition Dynamics
um if I go to the
if I go to that research what it is
essentially doing is evaluating the
posterior given a particular State and
an action J
so from my generative model I know that
if I start from this state and if I take
this action I go to this post areas and
I consider all the consequences and if
in the generative model it is unlikely
that if I go east I don't go there and
so on it's basically it's it's
automatically reflected in the expected
free energy
um so I hope that answers the question
so here
um if I set the action Precision to be
high
and
also enable the
environment
so initially I am in this particular
State and we with respect to the
expected free energy what I'm doing is
I'm using my generative model to predict
what will happen if I take four actions
and my predictions will say that if I
take North I will go here and if I take
all the other actions I stay here and
because in my prior preference North is
more preferred I can infer that not just
the
uh action I should go for so that's the
idea
so here the grid structure is given to
the agent and it might be a little
confusing but the agent can also learn
the script structure and if this will
work so once I know the grid structure
as an agent I can simulate the future
and consider the consequences of action
right
so that's what's happening and once I'm
in this state I will consider the
consequence of all four actions and I
will infer that okay
um going east is better because that
will take me to this state
so there's always a difference between
or you should keep in mind how
generative model and generative process
are two different things
and what the agent knows might not be
the reality or might be the reality
depending upon what you give it
um
so
if you were gonna go about
making a new
situation that you wanted to do
generative modeling for
do you tend to start from an existing
working Pi mdp notebook and start
modifying State spaces or do you draw it
out on a canvas like how would you
recommend somebody other than
replicating what is shown here let's
just say we're interested in something
that's not exactly just a maze what do
we do to get our head around
how we should proceed
yeah
good question so if you're trying to
simulate say a new environment you have
the heavy lifting to do which is to
define the generative model for the
agent
um you can either Define a various parts
generative model which the agent can
learn but you have to define the
structure that structure should be there
and only using the structure the agent
uh can learn the generative model so
here
um you can make use of this cell of code
to understand how I Define the structure
of the grid
okay so I am defining a structure for
the agent for it to make use of I'm
saying that there are 25 valid States
and there are four available actions and
this is the standard way of defining the
state space
in time DB and you also have to Define
um the Central parameters a b c and d
for the agent stimulations so here I am
defining
um a using my state space and
observation space but this step of
giving it or telling it that it's an
identity Matrix is my decision choice in
my modeling I don't have to do this for
simulations I can see if the agent is
learning it from a random a matrix or
when it starts from a random Matrix and
similarly for this B Matrix this
structure
is defined and there are functions like
this which can give you a random B
Matrix but this is a modeling choice
where if I want to give it the grid
structure or not give it the grid
structure I can start from a random V
Matrix let the agent learn and look at
that learned beam it just for the
purpose of the demo I gave it the grid
structure to enable it to take the
actions but it's not a mandatory thing
so this notebook is useful in the sense
that you know what to do but definitely
you should play around with steps that
may not be mandatory right so if I give
a prior preference for this state to be
the maximum then you can see behavior
that the agent will try and go there
right so
um this prior performance is defined uh
in conjunction that this is the goal
state but this may not be the cold State
and in a different task what prior
preference means is different according
to the environment
um right so that's also there and your
prior so once you define that generative
model which you have to do that's you
can't run from it then everything is
kind of automated the agent
um
only have to use the agent dot step give
it the observation from the environment
the agent knows how to take actions and
then everything that happens inside the
agent you don't really have to worry
um yeah
so this structure I'm sure will be
useful for your particular task
that you are trying to model in your
hmm
yes very interesting and how would you
contrast that or or point to any
similarities or differences with how
this would be pursued outside of active
inference like if somebody were just
going to use another kind of deep policy
agent in the Maze example
um what parts of the process would be
familiar
and what parts would be like a lot of
work that wasn't expected or skipping
through parts that were a lot of work
otherwise
yeah
um so the general structure is very
familiar to somebody who does things
like this in reinforcement learning so
um the idea that it's an agent dot step
and environment dot step so this is the
standard open AI Jim way of writing an
environment and a standard open AI way
of writing an agent okay so if you have
a queue learning agent who does the same
trying to navigate then the way you have
to define the Q Matrix is the heavy
lifting there it's just a state action
mapping and in contrast to that in
active inference you have to come up
with a generative model that you want to
see so in active inference it generative
model is the central thing right without
that without a generative model there is
no meaning of purposeful behavior in
active Independence so the only
unfamiliar part
for a person who's coming from uh say a
field like reinforcement learning is the
structure of the generating model but
there is no way other than getting used
to it where it's the form DP structure
which dominates but if you're doing deep
active inference all of this is going to
be neural networks and palm DPS are also
not active in prints
um things right it's a industrial
engineering thing so form DPS must also
be familiar for people who are coming
from the computer science background
just the idea that
um what really happens in the agent is
the active inference part where we have
expected free energies and variational
free energies and if you want to learn
about that then you have to go to the
agents and see how it works look at the
matrices numerically see what's
happening but I don't in in a level
where you want to get started I don't
see any problem all of this is
um
standard Frameworks like bomb DBS and
openai gym environments agent
environment Loop all this is very deeply
discussed in computer science it's not
cool
um so what what other um
motifs or cognitive phenomena are you
excited or how do you see the pi mdp
development trajectory continuing after
you're sophisticated inference gets
pulled in
yeah
um
so the IMDb had the original
functionality and
um the functionality to implement or
simulate
um General active inference agents with
the policy space and so on and that
enabled a lot of people in the community
who is not who are not
um
are familiar with
um complicated coding and so on who
people who do psychology Psychiatry and
and all the things right so whoever want
to come up uh and try Implement active
inference by mdp enabled that and I'm
I'm hoping that this module will enable
people who want to try out so stay great
inference experiments in their
particular domain so this if you spend
some time and get familiarize yourself
with the structure of how Pi mdp works
then everything else is just writing a
jupyter notebook with minimal code right
to simulate this so if you have a
particular task in your domain I don't
see a problem for a beginner to kind of
try and code it and what I am very
excited to see is people using this
module for variety of experiments just
like how people started using pi mdp and
sophisticated inference is taking off
and it's now widely talked about about
how it is
how it is the way of doing active
inference and I'm really hoping that
people in various domains start using
this module and see their experiments
and I look forward
yeah so what time DP did two years ago
I'm hoping this module will do to people
who are trying to uh model active
inference in this state
so you mentioned the open AI gym and the
standardized format and and what
benchmarks do you use or what are you
what kind of test Suites are you
comparing
and how do we really know when we've
made a generative model that
really exceeds or excels in a way that
other
um techniques are just not doing
yeah so if I um may go to the open AI
gym website
um we have several experiments there the
classical reinforcement learning
examples
um like the lunar lander that you see in
this screen right now so active
inference permits Inception has faced
problems of scaling
um to tasks and that has that's in
itself a field of research in active
inference
um scaling active in print and that's
one of the reasons why deep active
inference took over
um dealing with tasks like this so there
are benchmarks
um even now where the sophisticated
inference may not be able to deal with
State spaces and personally that's my
research in my PhD I am actually looking
at
um optimal optimizing computations in
sophisticated inference
algorithms that lets you scale up two
environments like that but to get
started you will have to kind of write
code and see if it works for an
environment then look at if it's not
working then you have to look at method
to scale it up and and so on so
if I am talking about benchmarks
sophisticated in Princess as good as any
RL algorithms
um for this state space so for small
problems so which Gate entrance will
work and it's really good but for high
dimensional problems like this
um the classical implementation that I
just showed might not work but it's good
enough for any decent experiment but if
you want to scale up then that's still
open and it's a new field of research
and what you do might become a next new
important paper right so that's all I
can tell in that regard
what measures do you think you'd be
looking for
like a computational resources or what
what are the measures that even make
sense to juxtapose
such different methods
yeah so the open AI gym was designed for
that to compare different uh algorithms
so open AI gym by definition is a
collection of many environments so in my
demo I was talking about the grid
environment
open aigm is nothing but a collection of
many environments which will let you
interact with those environments using
the environment dot step function
um
yeah so here we have the
environment.step function that will let
you interact with the lunar lander and
that particular task will have matrixes
that lets you
um judge how good or bad your algorithm
is so in this lunar lander problem how
optimally can you land your Rover
between these two flags by spending
minimizing the fuel and so on so those
matrices are very tasks specific and
that's One Direction you have to take
you can take uh try and compete with RL
algorithms in in matrixes but
um the right potential or the potential
IC in sophisticated inferences uh
modeling intelligent Behavior where in
RL the focus is to get things done to
make this work but it's not really
explainable especially deep RL and deep
learning methods but in active inference
if you manage to scale it up they are
explainable and and they are
um that will let you understand how
intelligent emerges with time and I I
see that more interesting than
um competing with RL because if your
focus is getting things done then maybe
engineering is the right way and not
active insurance
any other comments or thoughts
Osman do you have any other comments or
thoughts
no I I'm pretty happy I hope um I was
clear explaining the code maybe it was
too complicated or simple depending upon
your level
um but I hope it is useful to at least
one person who would start using this
and write the code and so thank you so
much for your time awesome thank you for
the opportunity then
thank you for joining till next time see
you
thank you so much bye
all right
greetings to Korea
until next time see you
you can um
mute the live stream or turn off the
other live stream but yeah thank you for
joining
yes uh thank you for uh inviting thank
you for it yeah
um well
we have a
little bit 35 or 38 minutes so it would
be awesome to uh have your presentation
right uh so
the moment uh
well
can you see my well
but I saw PowerPoint
okay uh
can you see my screen uh perfect perfect
okay
so shall we start yes thank you
okay oh then uh thank you for uh
organizing this wonderful uh Symposium
today I'd like to talk about a
relationship between canonical neural
network and
active inference and possible extension
uh or modern social on the shared
intelligence using canonical neural
networks so let's start
so uh as you know the free energy
principle is proposed by a car free
stand that states that perception
learning and action of all biological
organisms are determined to minimize the
variation of energy as a tractable proxy
for surprise minimization and by this uh
process
organisms can perform uh parational
Beijing inference or external mineral
state
and this is this cartoon just show one
example typical setup under the free
energy principle active inference here
there is a hidden state in the external
world and only a part of this state can
be uh observable for our agent this dog
and this transformation is done by a
genetic model parameterized
parameterized by Theta
and to in for the hidden state agent
need to reconstruct the copy of the
external State called posterior relief
and this optimization is done by
minimizing a variational free energy
and parameter is also optimized by
minimizing free energy to to obtain up
generating model to represent this
relationship an interesting aspect of
the free energy transplant active
inference is its application to the
optimization of action here our agents
have some preference prior C and to
obtain this observation in the future
agent May select the action that
minimize the expected free energy in the
future to to
to obtain the most predictable uh
outcome and finally by selecting uh
actions that minimize the expect
frequency it can obtain the feed
so this is a typical setup on the active
inference but question is what is the
neural noun substrate that can implement
this process so that that is our
interest and to address this issue we
propose a salary as borrowed here we
consider that uh external world is
parameterized characterized by a set of
the variables like this here this is a
posterior expectation and
as indicate the hidden state in the
external World Delta indicates the
action of the agent or decision and the
Theta
indicator parameter and the Lambda is a
hyper parameter so those uh set or so
parameters or variables characterize a
generative model and free energy
variation of energy is defined as a
function of the sequence of observation
and the external state and its
minimization indicates the variational
free energy operational elevation
inference uh
similarly we consider a dynamics of
neural network and we consider that a
Dynamics is characterized by a set of
those variables here x indicates that
neural activity by having great at the
middle area
neurons and the Y indicate near activity
of output radiant neurons and W here is
a synaptic weight and the Phi is the
other any other free parameter that
characterize the neural network and we
consider that neural network Dynamics is
characterized by minimization of some
cost function here this is a function of
the O and the Phi internal state of
neural network and
yo it's minimization indicate the
generation of neural network Dynamics
including both activity and plasticity
and our Theory indicates uh equivalence
between those two functions means that
for any neural network that minimize
some cost function error there is a
generative model that satisfy if we call
Air which means that uh
uh the
recapturation of external Dynamics is an
inherent feature of any neural system
that for such Dynamics so this is a
interesting prediction about the two
other struct
so I I would like to introduce some
analytically tractable example to
understand uh this relationship formally
so first we consider a very simple
architecture this is represented by a
pong DP without any stage transition so
hidden State s is simply
generated by prior distribution D and
it's uh it is a binary state but we
consider a vector of binary States so it
is a factor of factorial structure and
observation is also binary
vector and the transformation from s to
O is characterized by categorical
distribution uh using a regular Matrix a
and variational Beijing inference
indicate the inversion of this
generative process like this so by
solving the appropriate free energy
functional we obtain those uh posterior
brief that is the optimal in the
Bayesian sense
so on the other hand for neural network
we consider such structure uh here upper
part indicates the generation of signal
in the external world and the neural
network comprises only a single layer
here activity of output layer are
generated by a weighted sum of
sensory input or weighted by synaptic
Matrix W and we then characterize this
neural network
in the next slide
so uh to model neural neural network or
neuron
we start from considering project
equation which is the
four which comprises four differential
equation and this is a very complicated
non-linear equation and although it is
laboratory possible so we consider some
reduction of these equations so a
typical reduction method is
is like this for example M here is a
much faster than other variables so this
can be replaced with its fixed point or
it is known that H and minus one sorry
it is known that H and 1 minus is n is a
have a similar Dynamics so we we can
consider a new effective variable U to
characterize those two
variables and then we obtain to the
positive equation like this so this is a
a famous class of neural network model
which includes the well-known fixed View
and agreement model uh or other uh
continuous neural network model and we
we modify those models to to derive
canonical neural model so this is a
definition of canonical neural network
model here
leak current is characterized by inbus
sumoid function instead of a cubic
function which is a adopted in the fifth
few nagma model and we also consider a
connection uh synaptic connection and
this part indicate the synaptic input
from a sensory layer through uh weight
matrices and one may consider that W1
indicate excitatory synapse and w0
indicator hv3 synapse and the threshold
adaptives thresholds that are function
of WR and w0
interestingly when we consider the fixed
point of this differential equation we
obtain a well-known red coding model in
with the sigmoider activation function
so
which means that we can say that in some
sense this canonical neural network
model is a approximation of how you can
have three equation and its acts
approximation level is a
in some sense between the realistic
model and the most simplified red coding
model so we basically consider this type
of neural network model and in the next
slide we
consider what is the plausible cost
function or this neural network model
so again we
write the same equation for canonical
neural network model which represents
the activity of neurons and Vector of
neurons
and we consider cost function for this
differential equation which can be
obtained by simply
calculating the integral of uh right
hand side of this equation and get this
type of cost function for neural network
this is biological portable cost
function in the sense that its
derivative derived a neural network
activity which has a certain virus
called possibility
moreover
if we consider a derivative of this cost
function with respect to synaptic
weights w we obtain a conventional
cyanotic plasticity rule which follows
the hepian law
uh on the other hand for
Beijing inference we first Define
generality model uh like the previous
slide and
we then derive the sorry we then derive
a variational energy for uh given
generative model so this variation of
free energy is derived from the Palm DP
model in the previous slide and its
minimization indicates the page and
infrast and running
so we formed a
formal correspondences between a
component of those two cost functions
like this so this block Vector formally
correspond to this block Vector that
represents posterior expectation and
this logarithm correspond to this
logarithm
and actually this a matrix
can be represented as the block Matrix
like this and it's a DOT product uh
correspond to this computation and
finally uh these five uh naturally
correspond to this uh log D logo of
State prior so which means that uh
because the cost function uh same it's
derivative uh
provide the the
the
its derivative provides the the some
sorry so because the cost function are
formally equivalent it's derivative uh
it's uh sorry it's a it's a result of uh
derivative it also corresponding each
other so which means that uh for any
neural activity equation in this form uh
there is a corresponding Bayesian
inference equation this is a equation
that computes the posterior div of the
helium State and this synaptic process
equation format correspond to learning
or parameter or generative model and
moreover by establishing this
relationship we can consider the reverse
engineering of the genetic model from
empirical data here uh this uh
schematic
summarize our approach to reverse
engineer generative model and we we
first record the neural activity and
assign the canonical neural network to
explain this obtained data and by
Computing the integral we obtain the
cost function for this canonical Network
and by the mathematical equivalence we
established we can automatically
identify a genetic model and free
operational free energy that correspond
to this neural network architecture so
interestingly this is a Bayesian agent
which is a type of which is a kind of
artificial intelligence but importantly
this artificial intelligence is a
formally derived from empirical data so
we can say that this agent is a
biometric
integers that follow the pre-energy
principle
and then its derivative with respect to
a parameter posterior
derived synaptic plastic CR algorithm
that follow the free energy minimization
and it's time integral can predict the
running process or original neural
network
neural network
data so which means that if if the
friend as a principle is correct then
this prediction should work
should work and should be able to
predict the the result of this neural
data without referencing to the data
itself so our strategy is uh in summary
our strategy is that we
reconstruct genetic model only from the
initial data with like initial Data
before learning and then predict the
running process or running the curve
that this neural neural system should
follow
by using the free energy principles and
compare or examine where the this
prediction is correct uh by by comparing
uh capture data after running and the
prediction by the frequency principle
and if this prediction is correct then
it indicates the predictive validity of
the frequency principle and the setup
considered
okay
so we apply this strategy to the in
vitro neural network so here this in
vitro neural network are stimulated uh
using the form DP genitive process
defined in the previous slide so there
are two hidden sources that are binary
signals and they are mixture and they
are mixed to generate uh 32
sensory stimuli those are also binary
and this is a overview experiment uh by
by stimulating in vitural neurons so
they generate Spike spiking response and
those rhyme indicate a high density
spiking response so we of that uh
in some neuron
the response specificity
is so we found that uh
for some neuron
response was high to Source One
uh signal compared to Source 2 signal
and if we see the transition of uh those
neurons we found that although we we
remove the offset uh at the first
session uh to to set those activities
zero but we see that those neuron
self-organized to responds High when
Source one is one but not uh but those
neurons response low low level when the
source one is zero so which means that
those neural activity through the
neurons response uh was uh consistent
with our theoretical prediction that new
activity serve organized to encode the
posterior expectation of helium State
and we also found that some other group
of neuron response preferentially to
Source 2 but not to Source One
so then we ask okay then we we found
that posterior expectations encoded by
neural activity and the next question
what is other what about other neuronal
substrate and we then ask whether we
they ask if the
priority about hidden state is equal to
effectively equal to the firing
threshold of a neural activity model
yeah Network model uh so if the server
is correct this corresponds
correspondence should exist to check
this uh we we first simulated a Beijing
agent and when we evaluate the
priority of the Beijing agent uh the
inference was attenuated as I expected
and we warned that when we buried the
excitatory level of in vitro neural
network by using the pharmacological
manipulation we also found that uh
the attenuation the attenuation of
influence
so which is consistent with our
theoretical prediction that
firing threshold encode priority or with
the hidden State and
and next we consider whether the
synergic plasticity followed the
freenancy principle by asking whether
frequency principle can predict the
qualitative self-organization of a
subsequent uh
a
subsequent neural data
so here we model a neural neural neural
network like this there are two Ensemble
neurons that encode Source One and
Source two and we first compute the
effective synaptic weight of uh those uh
networks uh using a conventional
connection strings as mentioned approach
and the plot dot uh final equate on the
landscape or theoretically computed free
energy
so
so this is a trajectory of MP Curry
estimated
synapse weights effective synaptic
process synaptic connectivity and as
predicted uh those uh changes
reduce the the free energy
and here we computed this theoretically
predicted free energy landscape only
using the first 10 sessions data so that
this indicated
indicate some prediction of
of the self-organization
and uh for more explicit uh prediction
we then simulated a new activity and
plasticity using green as a principle
here
we uh here the brighter color indicates
the prediction of uh data without
referring to activity data so these
those lines uh
exactly follow the this frequency
gradient uh
and we found that this predicted
trajectory
is a title title correlated with this
empirically estimated effective synaptic
weights
and the earlier rate is uh practice
so it indicates that in the principle
can
uh quantitatively predict the serial
colonization in this setup so it
indicates some predictability of
different energy principle under this
sector
and then we also consider the modeling
of the neural modulation uh
using active inference it is well known
that synaptic process is modified by
various factors like dopamine or other
learning assets recording serotonin so
on and one interesting property of those
modulations that as even so dopamine was
added
after
associative plasticity was established
it can change the result of plasticity
in a post-hoc or retrospective manner so
it's a
it's in price some Association to the
reward and plus decisions so we model
this process using canonical neural
network so here we model the uh post
Hulk modulation of ABN plasticity using
uh this type of uh plasticity equation
and we also consider the recurrent
neural network structure and output
create for this network and we consider
that modulation occur at this
connectivity uh
a layer and then we found uh cost
functions that can derive those those
differential equations and then formed a
corresponding variational for energy and
GNT model so which means that this sort
of a neural network activity including
moderation of sinus plasticity exactly
follow the free energy principle and
some type of homedep generality model
and by using this we show that this uh
biological approachable
neural network model with a moderation
of heavy and plasticity can solve the
some sort of uh delayed reward task like
maze task
and then finally we would like to
discuss a possible extension to this
framework to the modern social
intelligence so uh to to infer our con
specifics uh
we we need to select an approach to
create a generative model or or our
partners depending on our partners so
this can be done by vegan model
Resurrection scheme and we a previously
proposed a model that can predict the
multiple valid forms using uh uh one big
generative model that comprises multiple
genetic moderates and this movie shows
uh prediction of uh
prediction of uh songs
so like this uh this modern nicely
identify which giant model is the best
to explain a given sensory input and
this process indicates the the and the
the model can correctly input the
appropriate model
and then imitate the song
by its own action
so
although in the previous work we didn't
discuss a detailed neuronal substrate
for this mixture generative model we now
be able to consider the uh
corresponding architecture for example
if we consider the modulation of module
neural module by
neuromodulator like dopamine it up add
an attentional filter and this
attentional filter can be explained by
uh
three Factor heavy and running rule
introduced the introduced in the
previous slide so again the this
modulation is a
worked as the post-hoc modulation no
past heavier plasticity and this
modulation can
optimize each model to represent one
generality model one General uh one song
in a mutually
mutually independent manner so through
this process it is possible to learn
multiple genetic model uh in a virtually
plausible manner so in summary we found
that the Dynamics of canonical neural
networks that minimize the cost function
can be
read as a minimization of variation of
her energy it indicates a frequency
principle is an explanation for this
type of neural network and we also
validate this prediction using some in
vitural set drop by showing that
and by showing that friend as a
principal can qualitate a quantitatively
predict the self-organization of
subsequent uh plasticity uh only using
the initial data
and as the modeling we can extend uh
those canonical Network modeling uh to
the
action generation another planning via
the delayed modulation of heavy and
plasticity
and finally we discuss a possibility to
extend this canonical model to Modern
the social or shared intelligence
to to interact with Mars per Partners so
that's all of my talks thank you for
listening uh this is acknowledgment our
collaborator and findings and our unit
are now recruiting uh
researchers so if you're interested in
free check
awesome thank you for the presentation
to kuya
um I'll just ask a few quick questions
from the live chat and a few other
things that come up so Dave says
takuya used the phrase after plasticity
was established
was his group able to modify EG increase
plasticity or is he saying merely that
it was shown that there is plasticity
or
yeah I'm not sure if I understand
correctly your question but uh those
groups showed that uh the group showed
that dopamine
adding dopamine after two seconds after
the association
occurred can change the the the the the
the the the magnitude of rusticity so
without
uh how to say uh
if dopamine are this addition was before
this Association then processity level
is low but uh after the dopamine Edition
after Association can change this level
can increase the plasticity
like this or like this so which indicate
the the post-hoc modulation
tool I think that answers it
um
well
what are you excited for or what are
your
hopes or or feelings on where the octave
inference ecosystem is at and where
we're headed in the coming months and
years
but so sorry uh
again please it's uh just what are you
excited about other than your own
research directions what are you excited
about in the active inference ecosystem
yeah so of course One Direction is the
the modeling of uh social interaction so
which is much a rich architecture than
uh the interaction between the static
environment so if both Asian Quran with
each other then uh many interesting
phenomena can be observed so we are
excited uh with modern uh Zords
phenomena using barot Square plausible
uh Network neural network model through
this equivalence
awesome
any last comments
any other comments that you want to make
awesome
thanks again for the presentation and
people should check out live stream 51
where you and I talked a few other times
and went into some of the details on
that work there's a really there's a lot
there it's really exciting
thank you
all right thank you
see you next time bye see you next time
bye
foreign
all right the next
session is going to be with Shanna
Dobson
this section is going to be called
dark Imaginarium shared intelligence as
an Infinity curiosity type
um
all message Shannon make sure that
everything's good with the audio
wow
great
talk so far welcome China how are you
doing Danielle doing good
um awesome well
please take it away thank you for
joining
awesome
you know if you see my screen okay
Yep looks perfect thank you
okay perfect hey everyone thank you so
much for the invitation it's such a
great honor to be here I'm learning so
much
I'll be talking about
um an idea I had called Dark Imaginarium
where I'm trying to make shared
intelligence the concept of that what I
call an Infinity curiosity type
so you were so gracious to link the
paper so anyone can find more details
um there on fill archive
so I want to start with an discussion
about ontological commitment so my first
question is might we re-examine our
ontological commitments
so in particular two of them one
um Sean Carroll said so amazingly what
cannot be known because it does not
exist so Sean Carroll says the
Heisenberg uncertainty principle is
often explained as saying that we cannot
simultaneously know both the position
and the velocity of any object but the
reality is deeper than that it's not
that we can't know position to momentum
it's that they don't even exist at the
same time
the second one I want to examine is
Lenny suskin's quote we are all behind
someone else's Event Horizon so suskin
has a brilliant idea of space-time
emergence as the entanglement of two
black holes and what emerges from that
is called computational complexity
so
the role is quantum so every Theory
should be derivable strictly from the
laws of quantum mechanics one is going
to give us the notion of shared two is
going to give us the notion of ecology
so what would an ontological commitment
to dark look like
so my continual goal as everybody knows
is to sustain a simultaneous experience
and to understand why I currently cannot
to sustain a simultaneous experience
would be to bypass the integrative
system recall Consciousness so how would
you attain a two Consciousness in the
sense of in category Theory or an end
Consciousness how would we actually
develop something called like a two
memory so my colleague Robert brettner
and I fleshed out something called an
awareness where we're sort of examining
this idea
Mike Levin and all have repeatedly shown
that planaria memory is not in the head
where is the memory is memory a
sustained superpositional of what and
also what's the structure of a nemesis
could you have a superposition between
memory and Analysis
so I had a small dialogue with Chris
Fields the amazing Chris fields and I
said you know what is the difference
between these two questions what is the
waking State and what does Consciousness
or could it be that these are entirely
separate questions
so we're sort of in a mess either way if
there is a difference in these questions
then it is possible to sustain a waking
State without consciousness
and or a conscious state in a non-waking
state
so imagine somehow being in a waking
State under general anesthesia well if
these are not entirely different
questions and we could contend that
Consciousness is a form of waking state
or something along the lines of a waking
State as a condition of a conscious
state so how can humans have deltaways
which are canonically indicative of
unconscious deep sleep and thus a
non-waking state in the REM State the
patterns of which are indistinguishable
from a waking state
so we all know that general anesthesia
something like a propofol can reduce the
polyrhythmic brain activity to one
uniform hum and we know there's as many
theories about what anesthesia does to
Consciousness as there are
anesthesiologists but we've repeatedly
positive Consciousness as the produce
State and I wanted to turn this idea on
its head like is consciousness so robust
or is it a delicate interference or is
it a delicate inference no we know
Beginnings are always tricky but what if
sleep was the proto-state
so if you know if life is oceanic and it
revolves from these deep pressures with
the pressure of of getting onto land
like squeeze the REM State into this
full-blown wicking state that we're
engaging in right now anybody who's
listening so the waking state would be
something like an acceptation which is I
think quite impressive
so it's in this mess that I attempt to
Define dark Consciousness as a mixed
frequency state of being self-aware or
conscious while simultaneously being in
a deep sleep specifically in three sleep
so the sleepless protostate is quite is
quite strange the REM brain activity is
indistinguishable from waking activity
and this sort of Enchanted it's
Enchanted me for a bit the only
difference is eye movements so either
blinking or versus lateral movement
so REM is naturally having mixed
frequency brainwave States but the nrn
states and the REM states are starting
to blur as delta waves are creeping into
the REM state
now they've also found that sleep is a
local phenomenon
so of course I'm going to ask the Shanna
questions so then who is sleeping who is
remembering who is dreaming lucid
dreaming is a Quantum superposition or
is it a superposition or an integration
so in a sleep State you know can then
can we sustain a simultaneous experience
so must be I be knocked out in order to
sustain this level of simultaneity
dreaming we know this characteristic of
unsynchronized brain activity
so is the question then
my eye cannot just seen a
multi-consciousness but my dark eye my
sleep I can
you can reframe this in terms of a
reporting mechanisms and say perhaps we
are conscious of things we don't think
we are conscious of
so let's talk about what is dark
um a canonical definition of a dark
Theory or anything like this is like
um you know Dark Matter does not
interact electromagnetically with matter
but I want to sort of play around with
another idea of dark
um coming from De loses logic of sense
something he calls the Paradox of
infinite becoming
and which I'm going to read on the next
slide so what if dark was the
simultaneity of a becoming that eludes
the present
let's hold on to that for a second is
darker resolution issue but resolution
is merely translation breaking
translational symmetry
so is dark a symmetry breaking issue
and if so what symmetry and are we
actually looking at the wrong symmetry
is dark a sustained Quantum
superposition that of what again is dark
of many worlds Branch as dark the
dolphin uni uni hemispheric sleep
mechanism
so I'll read from De loses logic of
sense Allison through the Looking Glass
involve a category of very special
things events pure events when I say
Alice becomes larger I mean that she
becomes larger than she was by the same
token however she becomes smaller than
she is now certainly she is not bigger
and smaller at the same time she is
larger now she was smaller before
but it is at the same moment that one
becomes larger than one was and smaller
than one becomes
this is the simultaneity of a becoming
whose characteristic is tulude the
present
and so far as it eludes the present
becoming does not tolerate the
separation or the distinction of before
after or of past and future it pertains
to the essence of becoming to move and
pull in both directions at once Alice
does not grow without shrinking and vice
versa so good sense affirms it in all
things there is this determinable sensor
Direction a paradox is the affirmation
of both senses or directions at the same
time I continue the Paradox of this pure
becoming with its capacity to elude the
president is called the Paradox of
infinite identity the infinite identity
of both directions or Senses at the same
time a future in past of the day before
and the day after of more and less of
too much and not enough of active and
passive and of cause and effect it is
language which fixes the limit the
moment for example at which the excess
begins but it is language as well which
transcends the limits and restores
instant to the infinite equivalence of
an unlimited becoming
hence the reversals which constitute
Alice's Adventures the reversal becoming
larger and becoming smaller which way
which way asks Alice sensing that it is
always in both directions at the same
time so that for one she stays the same
through an optical illusion
the reverse all of the day before and
the day after the present always being
eluded Jam tomorrow and jam yesterday
but never Jam today the reversal of more
and less five nights are five times
hotter than a single one but they must
be five times as cold for the same
reason the reversal of active and
passive do cats eat bats is as good as
do bats eat cats
the reversal will cause and effect to be
punished before having committed a fault
to cry before having pricked oneself to
serve Looking Glass cake before having
divided up the servings all these
reversals as they appear an infinite
identity of one consequence a contesting
analysis personal identity and the loss
of a proper name the loss of the proper
name is Adventure which is repeated
throughout Alice's Adventures hints
infinite identity
so I take this and I'm going to formally
Define dark Consciousness as a state of
being conscious while simultaneously
being in deep Sleep specifically in
three where dark is going to be a
two-fold hybrid the simultaneity of
infinite identity and of a becoming that
eludes the present so let's reconstruct
the dark Consciousness version of De
loses Paradox of pure becoming for Alice
in dark Wonderland and through the dark
Looking Glass okay when I say Alice
becomes sleepy I mean that she becomes
sleepier than she was by the same token
however she becomes more self-aware than
she is now
certainly she's not asleep and
self-aware at the same time she's asleep
now
she was self-aware before but it is at
the same moment that one becomes
sleepier than one was a more self-aware
than one becomes
so dark Consciousness I contend would
take place in something called like a
dark time this is going to get weird so
uh Chris fields and I talked about
entropic time where a time where
learning exceeds forgetting so we all
know that linear time is based on the
linear ordering property of the positive
integers okay so what would be the
structure of a time that does not
interact electromagnetically with this
waking State interface
so like AI must pay attention all the
time would this sort of be like a dark
time sleep is local time is local we
know what how beautiful a Time crystal
is so time Crystal you know has a
structure that is periodic in time
can you play with that and say time is
periodic and what
so if we've explained that dark is not
concerned with these Notions of before
and after then we would want a notion of
time that can support the Paradox of
infinite identity with a notion of
duration that is one of self-similarity
so we can tend that dark Consciousness
would occur in something like a periodic
time which was a time based on the P
attic number system periodic time would
measure periodic duration
okay it's been on all right so there
exists few objects more Looking Glass
than a piatic clock well maybe piatic go
and collabi out chess and perfectoid go
but after all the periodic numbers have
no notion of linear ordering their shape
resembles a sierpinski triangle which is
a self-similar set
hmm so this periodic time is not
concerned with Notions of before or
after that is a periodic time does not
tolerate the separation or the
distinction of before or after of past
or future
so because the Pediatric topology is one
of total disconnectedness periodic time
is more like a time of now continual
zooming in to more and more now
thus periodic time measures periodic
duration through its fractal properties
of zooming in
so let's try to look at a piano clock
all right so Pi time can take two forms
the canonical periodic time defined on
the previous slide and also topological
periodic time which builds into its very
structure the piatic topology of
periodic time
so there would only be one unit of time
in periodic time we should call the
Archimedes this is the periodic
valuation so you can think of hour
equals periodic valuation equals the
Archimedes how strange it is to have
only one unit of time
topological periodic time measures
duration topologically as total
disconnectedness so the unit of time on
topological periodic time is what I call
the pitopo so we State this formula
there's only one unit of time in
topological periodic time called the
pitopo
so a topological hour equals a periodic
topology called a p Topo so given such a
periodic clock
let us imagine the seasons in periodic
time Panic snow Panic ring mean piatic
weather types and piatic rainbows
daylight savings time could take the
form of changing the p in the piatic
this could be very drastic
but imagine pediatic metabolics periodic
ATP and pediatic DNA imagine periodic
cognition types like piatic memory
piatic font piatic attention learning
and pediatric perception imagine a
pediatic Looking Glass imagine through
the periodic Looking Glass
so it's pivot to fep what does ivp
actually specifically say about Dark
Matter even dark in the way that I'm
using the term is there a free Dark
Energy principle
how can we strictly derive sleep from
quantum mechanics according to fep does
dark energy actually exhibit
entanglement how do we test this we
should be able to derive the entire
active inference formalism straight from
quantum mechanics alone uh by way of
entanglement entropy some form of
quantum gravity can we do some sort of
dark General adversarial Network
um to look at something like a dark
brain we all know that lower
lateralization in the brain is often
associated with schizophrenia or you
know people like Einstein or someone
with a large parietal lobe probably like
myself any mathematician and what
Universal lateralization look like
um
I think dark neurons would take the form
of something like you treat the neuronal
networks as algebraic curves or isogeny
graphs you talk of neurons in terms of
their properties as varieties so you're
actually bringing the heavy machinery of
algebraic geometry into neurology and my
big goal is to actually create something
like a neuronal Time Crystal so that
shared intelligence would actually be a
periodicity in time
I'm not there yet so until I get that
and it's like well let's just let's try
to model these wild mixed frequency N3
plus self-aware states of dark
Consciousness dark mathematics is having
a coin it's gonna it's like a biomimicry
which mimics dark energy does not
interact electromagnetically with matter
you have to find the mathematical
equivalent of that so I think you can do
something like a dark dilethyism or just
make a model that is modeling the mixed
frequency states which is what I'm
trying to which is what I tackle on the
first in the paper so we've previously
shown that Intrepid categorizations are
condensed sets condensed sets form a
topos so in the paper I outlined the
construction of three potential
mathematical models of this means of
these mixed frequency N3 sulfur States
um you can do dark Consciousness as a
dark two pose which is a graph indeed
two posts there's a two category of two
sheaves over two site elucidate just a
little bit dark Consciousness is a
perfectoid length space in the sense of
shows or as a diamond-like space Also in
the sense of Schultz so I contend that
the two sheath structure can actually
model the mixed frequency state of dark
Consciousness the N3 self-aware State
and the Sheaf is a one stack again which
is a sheath that takes values in
groupoids not sets so this is already
radically different and consider a two
category of two sheaves so two category
consists of objects you have the one
morphisms between the objects and you
have the two morphisms between the one
morphisms you can keep going three
category up to n category
so this two category of two sheaves
would have two sheets as the objects one
more fisms between the two sheaves two
morphisms between the one morphisms and
so using that structure I think that you
can actually model one morphisms as what
I'm going to call dark reflexivities uh
these are going to be your local
coherency States and then two morphisms
are actually two inferences which are
going to be Global coherency States
amongst the mixed frequency States
so a lovely property called Morita
equivalent science states that
inequivalent sites have equivalent Chief
toposes and I do believe that that's the
main property you need to get this local
Global Behavior around neural networks
so if you actually wish to model the
mixed frequency clusters as fractals
exhibiting some kind of self-similar
behavior then you can use this Rich
structure perfectorate spaces and are
there sparkling successor the diamond so
just a quick definition let perf that'd
be the subcategory perfectoid space is a
characteristic p a diamond is a pro atel
sheath on the site perf written as this
quotient of a perfectoid space X by a
pervatel equivalence relation
so a perfectoid space is going to be
this attic space in the sense of Huber
that's covered by athenoid spaces of the
form Spa R plus where R is a perfectoid
ring and then points of spa which is the
attic Spectrum R Plus or equivalence
classes of continuous valuations on r
um summer National Sly diamond and you
give incredible um explanation that was
a parallel to a mineralogical diamond
so you can let C be an algebraically
closed ethanoid field geometric points
Spa C to D is made visible by pullback
along a quasi-provital cover that
results in profiitely many copies of spa
C so you're making a geometric Point
visible as profinely many copies that
was invisible before does the following
parallel with a mineralogical diamond so
the interior points are made visible as
impurities which Sparkle as colorful
Reflections on the many sides of the
diamond
so
um you can also do something maybe like
a dark diamond redesignated functor is
dark as a means to actually let's go the
other way and see the impurities so then
you're going to take the geometric Point
make it visible Maybe by a pushed
forward along with positive prototype
cover resulting in periodically many
copies of small C
right so um a diamond is a they're using
a diamond as a Sheaf but a sheath in
terms of a functor of points so the
diamond spot QP is a functor from the
category perv to the category sets you
literally fix the perfectoid space and
look at the home sets of X into the
diamond and so you know the technically
the scheme is then said to represent the
functor
so I want to Pivot to in Booking AI in
this thing so my colleague and I Julian
scape are coming up with um something I
call I've coined the qubit pedagogy
which is going to be a new model
pedagogy that is actually infused with
heavy principles of quantum mechanics
and so that with these um we've we've
created these Quantum intrinsic
curiosity algorithms that are feeding
into the aqubit pedagogy and based on
those the Curiosity algorithm algorithms
I've designed three dark versions so
what I call the dark planaria curiosity
algorithm it's a curiosity type it
enables encourages the AI to explore
patterns of a planaria regeneration the
AI would develop Quantum air correcting
codes which mimic planaria regeneration
so dark one the second one would be dark
Quantum reality monitoring Network this
is a curiosity type it'll courage
encourage AI to explore dark reflexivity
is what I call fractal identity AI would
create models of n reflexivity in the
sense of n category that's a new type of
reality monitoring of fractal identity
in a dark contrast state the last one
would be some sort of dark Quantum N3
and REM curiosity algorithm this
curiosity type is going to encourage AI
to explore superpositions of various
brain patterns in rem states to predict
new types of N3 delta waves that could
emerge in rem States so imagine AI could
then develop new stages of REM sleep
such as like one REM two REM of two and
REM which is a very which is which is a
clever limit and play on nram anyway the
AI could also develop new dark cognition
types that correlate with the new types
of delta waves
substitutional fractal identity seems
odd but I do contend that objects living
in fractal time the correspondingly have
fractal identity
it's a concept of outlined as follows so
fractal identity has a reflexivity
relation that is fractal so the very
canonical loop the loop relation of an
agent reporting back to itself I report
back to me would be fractal and how
strange is that so fractal identity
would not suffer the same problems with
continuity over time
um since the time in which it exists has
no linear ordering it would definitely
suffer different problems but continuity
over time is something Chris fields and
I have been like how do you how do you
explain that
um so you can best model the fractal
identity properties as perfectoid-like
or diamond-like there and construct a
notion of reflexivity as a perfectoid
space the spaces are extremely
rich structure but like kind of
difficult but if you want to model
fractal identity I think you should use
them so this we create new concepts of
perfectoid reflexivity diamond
reflexivity so in in reflexivity the
reflexivity relation could now be an in
stack thus in reflexivity is an in-stack
perfectoid spaces
so here comes the culmination of this
talk which is about shared intelligence
is what I've coined the dark Imaginarium
so imagine an AI that could C
simultaneously compute the infinity
category of every concept
you know having some Quantum computation
around to help the computational
complexity what um you know uh not be
that so dark Imaginarium is what is
going to be what I call um an Infinity
curiosity type so Infinity curiosity
sites this is a higher order curiosity
AI algorithm that encourages the AI to
think in Infinity categories so that is
it actually encourages the AI to
construct an Infinity category as its
means of higher order inference so
objects are higher dimensional data sets
the AI the AI would seek out higher
order n morphisms between the objects
and then morphisms between the morphisms
so such dark Imaginarium is a meta
curiosity algorithm that can create its
own Infinity curiosity algorithms and
they're in creating curiosity types of
the complexity that super fascinating
most likely unknown to humans so it's
functorial
um what can what can dark Imaginarium do
well the AI would develop inversions of
current brain waves in their hybrid
combinations it could develop in Delta
wave in Theta wave and Alpha wave and
beta wave and in gamma wave for n equals
zero one all the way up like a two gamma
wave that's structurally resembled a two
category a three beta wave that's
structurally resembled three category an
AI could develop new types of waking
States and new types of sleep States
based on the combinations of these
beyond the standard in one and two and
three in rem and one REM
AI could develop an end waking State an
nrem State uh you know a three REM stake
consists of three and one three and two
three and three imagine an end dolphin I
was capable of in hemispheric sleep
State and other exotic life forms right
what else could it do well it could
develop new geometries for the brain
patterns and for currently existing
brain patterns typical shapes include
sinusoidal non-solusoidal saw2 spindle K
complex but maybe this AI could develop
3D and 4D versions of the canonical wave
patterns like a tesseract gamma wave so
but also the AI could develop entirely
new brainwave geometries that correspond
complex surfaces like a riemann's
surface colavia Yao manifold or
algebraic variety
so there I could build new cognition
types other than the standard five it
could produce incognition types such as
infant inattention in perception in
learning in memory so it could also
predict non-human species cognition
types such as octopus thought or
dragonfly attention lastly you can
produce hybrid combinations of cross
species cognition types such as like
Optimum memory or Dragon man perception
and then it would encourage the AI to
develop new senses so you could develop
one stack versions of human senses
um like two seeing two hearing two
tasting two touching two smelling each
of these two senses once again take
values in groupoids and not sets so you
could develop instances of non-human
senses as well and hybrid combinations
like two shark human smell
so since the aics and morphisms between
the various and minus one morphisms the
AI can seek to develop new language
models based on higher order inference
types so from these inference models the
AI will explore Infinity languages and
develop extensive prototypes you could
use advanced mathematics to create new
models of time that could support the
new language models like two topos time
Diamond time and then the AI would seek
to develop new fractal identity types
from the language models and it could
design Advanced fractal Prosthetics such
as a two-ear or a 2i to extend cognition
so let's go a little bit further about
this extending cognition these are just
a few examples of what dark Imaginarium
could conceive of so we could continue
positive perfectoid version of this
using these new cognition types mental
States and brain waves new geometries we
can construct new patterns of thinking
which would support neurodiversity in
thinking so as said shared intelligence
this is how I'm seeing it would be
re-examined is this Infinity curiosity
type you can go even further and
construct a new concept of in shared
intelligence so you'd have a zero shared
intelligence a one shared intelligence
and as well as the New piatic Concept of
like P shared intelligence for p equals
two three four using piatics let's go
further right we repeatedly contend that
one way to help Advance the way we think
to extend human cognition is to upgrade
the number systems upon which the
canonical concepts are built upgrade
them to piadic perfectoid diamond-like
versions unless we get me thinking so
imagine like a Braven wave pattern that
resembles a collabio manifold could we
actually reverse engineer the levels of
conscious activity that could create
such a rhythm how about mixed frequency
brainwave patterns that resembled a
perfectoid diamond
what about an an in DNA molecule shape
like a collabio enfold or an in ATP
molecule or an in exciton condensate
structured like a collabigo and fold so
clearly different geometries of the
fundamental molecules and processes of
life would give rise to vastly different
fundamental units of life and
metacognition types the question is can
we use dark Imaginarium to reverse
engineer the complex life forms of
rising from such extraordinary
structures and the more and more complex
cognition patterns
what about a general adversarial Network
that's tweaked and has Infinity
categories you have two Infinity
categories talking to each other
developing their own language now Gan is
adversarial using a generator and a
discriminator with two neural networks
contesting by a zero-sum game what about
a collaborative Network so can we
construct a gcn containing two
diamond-like Infinity curiosity types
and paradiamond with a dark diamond
with a Quantum curiosity algorithm and
its reinforcement learning so shared
intelligence is this Infinity curiosity
type shared intelligence GCM could
create Infinity languages that are
superpositions of the diamond dark
diamond and be getting new models of
intelligence you know higher order
simultaneous computations by Quantum
curiosity would go by Maybe by homotopia
instead of as cost functions
so it's futurecast just for a second
um what is the end of a bill and the
what is the inevitability of dark
ecosystems mathematics of shared
intelligence what can a piatic Infinity
curiosity type prophecy
is every perfectoid space Diamond two
topos encoding the mixed frequency
patterns of an incognition type
in future work you may develop dark
mathematics using perfectoid diamonds as
dark diolethism aligning with a
structurally dark with what is
structurally
so while we currently cannot perfectly
model dark Consciousness perhaps one day
one dark day mediated by the dark
Imaginarium we will have the ethos and
the quantum computational complexity to
do so
thank you
thank you Shawna amazing presentation
I'll just quickly read some comments and
see if you have any thoughts from from
the great comments so Scott David
says
I love the presentation lots of fodder
for rumination thank you for inviting
these Concepts into an intriguing
choreography perhaps dark energy is our
perception of the fact of information
increase under free energy principle
processes and since the universe is made
of information dot dot dot
foreign
Scott thank you so much yeah I think you
should um yeah I think dot dot dot is um
is a beckoning that you should or we
should work on that idea I absolutely
agree
I'm glad you're inspired with these
Concepts um I don't really know where
they go but hopefully it's portals to
something like that
great effort one one more Scott David's
question does fractal identity reveal
the recursivity of rhetoric language
Consciousness informing individual
identity from Community identity inputs
yeah that's wonderful so yeah my um my
own thought is like what is an
individual identity right Scott so the
the reflexivity curve is always sort of
stumped me how there's so much distance
between I and me
um and so it assumes this notion of
continuity over time and so we've I've
always said what sort of notion of time
are we talking about to even have a
consistent identity somehow you always
wake up and everything is still here
somehow you wake up and you're not a
lobster I don't really understand how
that works you know but um yeah that's
nice if if you could use fractal
to get something singular from something
communal that might be cool but maybe
fractal is something sort of like
you're both at the same time
and that's what I don't know yet so I
think it's a totally revolutionary
thinking to not have a before or after
so if you can construct identity without
before or after then that's sort of what
I'm trying to do
but yeah that's cool if you want to get
identity from communal I think you can
do that they may also sort of um
Allure
well this is truly
food for thought
and uh I really hope people can
live with the darkness take it and run
with it because there's so many fun ways
to go
thank you so much I hope so too
so you're always welcome back thank you
and talk to you later
much bye good night
all right
bands
onto the last
session of the first interval greetings
Nikki
greetings
hello good morning yes good morning
how goes it
yeah I'm doing fine thanks
um would you like to present it then
we'll discuss
uh yes that sounds like a good idea
great
um let's see
just going to share my screen
yes
can you see the presentation
uh not yet
okay let's see what's next
Yep looks perfect
okay great
um
yeah should I do stocks yeah go for as
long as you want and then anyone can ask
questions in the live chat and I'll
write down some things too thank you
okay great
um yeah yeah so my uh presentation today
will be will be on advances in machine
theory of mind and a theory of my
sophistication
um
I'm currently a student at the
University of Amsterdam and finishing my
Master's pieces on this topic and I'll
be giving a broad overview of burn
machine theory of mind
um
and
um an idea or concept for an active
inference approach based on a previous
work related to active inference theory
of mind
um so to start
okay sorry
Okay so
for a global overview we'll start with
giving a short basic definition of what
theory of mind is and how it's been used
um then I'll give you a global overview
of current approaches
um to designing machine Theory mind
um including evasion approaches
approaches using biophysical models Etc
um then I'll zoom into active inference
models of theory of mind and social
intelligence and collective intelligence
more broadly
um and I'll get into the issue of fear
of my sophistication
um which is basically the depth of
recursivity
um
of beliefs that you can have about
another person's mental states and their
their thoughts or beliefs or goals about
you
um and then we'll get into the issue of
how to implement recursive beliefs and
as an example we'll discuss Bayesian
theory of mind
with K levels of depth
and then we'll get into the more
specific Paradigm that I'm using right
now to build a state of mind model
which is
based on a very simple model of the
matching panics Paradigm so we'll talk a
little bit about that and then we'll get
into the model itself and current ideas
for implementing uh theory of my
sophistication using active inference
um so first of all
what is theory of mind
um fear of mind has been introduced by
the very famous paper by primac and Port
Jeff in 1978.
um I think it was called does the
chimpanzee have a theory of mind
um and they define fear of Mind as the
ability to impute mental States
to himself and others as a system of
inferences
and they say system of inferences of
these clients probably do you properly
viewed as a theory first because such
states are not directly observable
because and second because the system
can be used to make predictions
specifically about the behavior of other
organisms
um and I think there's already a lot in
this definition and a lot of authors
looking at their mind right now uh still
use the same view of theory of Mind as a
theory a structured Theory
um of different kinds of mental states
such as goals beliefs and desires
um that facilitates facilitate the
prediction of the of observable behavior
in other agents such as spatial
Expressions movement or speech
um
[Music]
and that's yeah I find it very
interesting
um how how much this aligns with uh
maybe a predictive processing view of
social permission
um but also how yeah how weird it is
that
um that this Theory theory of theory of
mind is still so widespread
um in the theory of my literature
modeling literature so there's been some
discussion on
um whether you can properly regard
serious mind as a theory and if so what
kind of theory it is
um So within the philosophy of mine
they've been
basically two mainstreams
um or main perspectives and theory of
Minds according to the plastic Theory
theory of Tom fear of mine is a cause of
fear of how these internal mental States
generate other agents behaviors so it's
the same kind of view that we just saw
um and then the opposite side is called
simulation theory of theory of mind
which posits that we use the same kind
of cognitive and neuronal resources for
understanding and predicting other
agents as though those that we use for
understanding the cell and simulation
Theory can also take on different forms
and just the sun is coming up okay nice
to them so
um that's why I'm breathing light at the
moment
um but basically a lot of versions of
this some process that we use the same
kind of action prediction mechanisms for
ourselves for others
um and there is this new version of
simulation Theory and that Gordon
proposes in 2021
which very broadly says that the
um we have the same kind of theory for
other agencies for ourselves so there's
this generous theory of what it means to
be an agent and that is refined at
different stages to facilitate complex
sensitive predictions in social
interactions
um
so this is also interesting to look at
when you model theory of mind what kind
of a
um what two things theory of mind is and
how the specifically implementing
um so why would we be interested in
creating computational models of theory
of mind and so I think there are three
um important reasons why this is very
relevant at the moment first of all
there is a technical reason or the
reason of technological advancement
um there's been
um
some proposals that
um argue for
for the development of artificial social
intelligence
or waiting
yes
so
the technical reason for
um
for developing computational models of
theory of mind is to improve artificial
social intelligence especially as
when we start to live in a world in
which research on human AI interaction
becomes more relevant
um and that's been in this paper by
Williams for example that's argued that
improving artificial social intelligence
is needed for successful AI human
cooperation and it could improve
communication trust and maybe also value
alignment
um by utilizing theory of mind for Value
language for example
and there is a very strong foundational
reason to study social conditioning
generally
um and the evolution of social cognition
um for in silica hypothesis testing and
clarifying the conceptual boundaries of
theory of mind
um one great example for this is
research by divanadol which use a
computational model of recursive theory
of Minds
um compared to alternate models to study
a different cognitive strategies in
non-human primary primates
and they find no evidence for the
hypothesis that theory of Mind
sophistication involved with an increase
in her size but they do find a
correlation with for example neocortex
ratio
um so in this way yeah their theory of
Mind models can give us some insight
into the evolution of social cohition
um on the clinical side
um theory of Mind models can be used to
understand relevant social variations in
clinical calculations for example
through computational phenotyping and
Diagnostics and by studying social
behavior in groups that have some
difficulty
um with social interactions
um and Crews that shows some kind of
variation
a social cognition such as people with
Autism Spectrum
people in the autistic Spectrum people
with ADHD or schizophrenia
so I hope that with some of these
reasons I am convinced you that moving
theory of mind is very
um relevant at the moment and there have
been a lot of people already on this
um and
I've created this um
very Global overview of some approaches
that are that are representative or some
models that are representative of their
more General approaches
um
there's this
um ringtone model which aims to
basically build up fear of Mind
abilities and uh abilities facilitate
his social interaction from the bottom
up using biophysical models of neurons
firings
um that's why I've placed it on the
dynamic scale so I've aligned try to
align these modeling approaches along
the axis of have a trip time
um how broad the description is from the
individual level to maybe describing
what broader social and cultural
processes and along the level of
description from the molecular eye
physical to the behavioral
um and one thing you can see is that
there is a lot of work based on Invasion
inference and active inference that
moves along that has relevant ties to
but to the molecular and neurobiological
level but moves along the lines of
making behavioral and cognitive
predictions
um and there is very there are very
little models that really
um also
formalize the concrete implementation of
theory of mimes
um and there is also I think this need
for connecting
um this dynamic
implementational level
two individual level social permission
and putting that in the context of
social interaction more generally so
some of the representation
representational approaches that I've
selected are the tall Nets which is
which basically uses a neural network
embeddings to train reinforcement
learning agents we have a k Tom which is
evasion recursive model which I'll come
back to later
um some or theory of mind with self
other modeling
uses multi-agent reinforcement learning
with Goal inference and we have the more
theoretical active inference model of
implicit cultural learning course
thinking through a device which could be
seen as an alternative or a redefinition
of theory of mind
um
okay
so to sum up
um we have this stream of biophysical
models
um most notably brain tone which was
developed by Xiao at all
um and his strength are its
neurobiological plausibility and making
Dynamic predictions
um about neural oxidation and in
that's been
um populations that are associated with
uh theory of Mind abilities and its
weaknesses is that it's
quite computational quality and it it's
probably difficult to implement in an
interactional setting
um
this there's some deep learning models
such as tongnets by rabinovitz and serve
other modeling which I just mentioned
um that are also quite neurobiological
and also make some Dynamic predictions
um but there is this strong danger of
shortcuts which has been addressed in
deep learning models
um that the tasks might not be solved by
learning the relevance ability of being
able to infer another Asian schools or
beliefs
um but just by learning a simple lower
level associations between for example
the perspective or the
um this how another agent stands and
where for example a single reward would
be so there are a lot of ways to solve
the task and then assist finding that
deep learning models sometimes these
these kinds of shortcuts
um so that's something that's needed to
be addressed
um then there are some Beijing
belief-based models such as Ketone
um for
for recursive theory of mind
um and the Asian Tom which was
originally developed by Baker at all in
2011.
um and its strengths are that it's quite
efficient it's very easy to interpret
and its weaknesses are that it that
could brought to the implementational
level is longer and it requires many
priorities
um and there's this question about
whether it's stateable because of the
pro specifications that you have to give
um okay so as one of the I think the
interesting newer developments on a
theory of mind uh it's
yes
um
is a hierarchical active inference for
collaborative agents which has been
recently published
um
and taika is based on variation theory
of Mind by Baker at all but it adds this
formalization of the leaf resonance
which is the incorporation of beliefs
about another's intentions with top-down
predictions
um and this influence of these other
agents beliefs are modulated by
susceptibility parameter which controls
this influence
um and what I find so I think it's
important thing out here that they used
an approach based on asset inference but
it's not the they don't use the spare
energy principle for example
um so they do couple perception and
action but just in a different way using
a common filter so the way that
formalizes is slightly different but I
think the overall structure can still be
um yeah informing or inspiring for
active inference and Essence
um
so what is interesting about their
um simulation results is that they show
that agents
um that there's some emerging
collaboration on tasks for local use of
this susceptibility parameter without
any explicit planning or communication
needed and this means that they improve
upon the original Bayesian model which
explored um different sort of overall
plans for all of the agent which means
that an agent employing the Asian Top
would need to reason
um about the rules of all of the other
agents and which was very costly and
they were and the authors wanted to
improve on that team model maybe on the
Fly coordination which is more
spontaneous and takes less time
um and they also show that incorporating
the least resonance has a very positive
effect in scenarios in which there's
unbalanced information they did this
examination the overcooked domain in
which agents have to have agents have to
collaborate on different cooking class
and the goal is basically to order the
cooking order
um and then the intention would be any
kind of action that has to do with
completing the order
um and they show that incorporating the
leaf resonance
um is especially it seems to be
especially useful in situations with
antennas information which for example
One agent knows the order and the other
doesn't
um and these agents develop some kind of
leader follower Dynamic
um in which one is most sensible to the
other agent's intentions and one agent
attempts more to the evidence
um from from the environment
and this also aligns with what we know
about here it might mainly being
employed in situations in which shares
some asymmetry in what the agents know
about the environment
so I thought it was very
um insightful
cool
okay so I'm going to
um go into
uh some active influence approaches that
I think are relevant for developing
activated Spirit mind uh first of all
there's this very real proposal on
inculturation and normal developments
thinking for other Minds a variational
approach to cognition and culture which
we'll go into a little bit uh we'll go
into a castle and past paper on ideas
for spreading a free energy proposal for
Community cultural Dynamics
um will go into Kaufman adults model on
prolexive intelligence and finally also
the uh proposal by muchuses at all on
Beijing inferences about the self and
others
okay so first of all
I am starting with based inference about
the cell and others
um because it gives the very sort of
full introduction to I think predictive
social cognition and that's also why
I've added this figure on the right
um that is from the time in Fulton Bank
in 2018 which explores
um the social the predictive social
brain
um and what kind of features
um seem to be
seem to be relevant for categorizing and
understanding of its behaviors
um
some figure on the right you see that
there's a space this trade space which
is Odin by power such as sociality and
balance
um and that constraints the state space
which seems to be ordered by a
rationality social impact imbalance and
courses are just correlations but these
future seems to be the most predictive
of what they're seeing in the brain
um and you can see that there is this
sort of
um
yeah uh basically it's a very strong
top-down constraints of the possibility
space
in which you interpret other people's
actions
and you can also see that based on
another agent's actions you learn
something about where they where they
fall uh within the state space in a
given context and also where they form
the trade space what kind of so
um at the same time you might have
already have some priorities on what
kind of a person this is
um but you're also learning about it uh
you might also have some careers on how
someone behaves when they're not for
example or when they're sociable versus
unsociable and all these kinds of cry is
informative prayers they inform your
predictions in the context and they make
this task and much more manageable of
predicting other people's behaviors on
the Fly
um and I still think that links very
well and
um that team which is this proposal
which is that which is basically that
inference is about the self and others
at different time skills facilities
interpersonal minimization of surprise
um and thereby optimal social decision
making
so these uh and these self and other
representations first
um that are the facilitates
um personal minimization of surprise
um could be seen as representations that
inform uh our our inferences and
predictions on the thigh
[Music]
um
I think yeah I think it's also important
to mention that one of the main
addiction points of their paper is that
um that self-representation so beliefs
about how beliefs about the cells self
um can uh facilitating personal
minimization of surprise so even what I
think about me and how I represent that
while communicating will facilitate the
other person's uh optimal decision
making at that moment
um maybe life is by providing the right
kind of information that they need to
Ultimate um
okay so to the next uh two interesting
papers obvious we're spreading
um and an active infrast model of
collective intelligence so the key idea
I think for for both of these papers is
the emergence of career behaviors from
local interactions for customers this is
the global uh group behaviors cultural
truth and transmission or a transmission
of beliefs and homes and they describe
this process as the mutual achievement
of actively inferring agents through
communication and theory of mind is one
of the many mechanisms that facilitate
this process of achievement so that's
the link and they showed that the spread
of certain kinds of beliefs through a
group ending models just by making
agents interact in um in dyadic groups
um and stiminally uh Craftsman adults
show that
the system you can create system of free
energy minimizing agents with some
minimal uh properties of social
intelligence such as the ability to
assess how it's self-similar another
region is to themselves and the ability
to inspire another agents intentions
um and the ability to align their goals
to another agent more or less
um and they show that if you put all of
these agents together in those diets
they don't only minimize your energy on
the dietic field but they also minimize
free energy as a collective
and thereby this could this is a very
simple model of how adaptive behaviors
adaptive group behaviors could emerge
from Agents with very simple social
abilities
okay
so um now we get to thinking throughout
the Mayans
um which is not technically
um a proposal for fear of mine but it's
the proposal for how
um
social cognition
shapes inculturation more generally and
what kind of abilities agents
need to facilitate this kind of known
formation
um
and I think it's a very
yeah interesting proposal because
um I think it highlights an important
function of social behavior more
generally
and you could even see it as a way to
redefine theory of Mind as more of an
interactional concept than as an
individual level cognitive ability
um so according to this proposal singing
through other Minds is a property of
multiple interactive energy minimalizing
agents and a process by which agents
infer other agents expectations and
based on this the authors propose a
definition of enculturation as a process
of learning social expectations through
the selective passening of attention
that guides agents towards relevant
affordances within their social and
cultural Niche
um I'm not sure if you're all familiar
with the concept of affordances but it
was quite hyped up a couple of years ago
in general it is defined as the
relational construct denoting
possibilities for Action
um offered by an environment that are
code determined and also by an agent's
interests goals and abilities so I think
the the standard example for this is
when you are thirsty
um a glass of water might appear as an
affordance or you might not consciously
or Michael's attend to it otherwise
otherwise
um and cultural sport instance
um in this sense are epistemic
affordances
um so for instance that gives you some
epistemic value that have come to stand
out as reliable and relevant based on a
history of cultural information they
encode and good examples for this are
different kinds of signs of traffic
signs and we learn what they mean from a
young age and we sort of inherited the
symbolism of the church science and they
guide our
they guide our attention towards points
in traffic and they regulate our
behaviors
um
so when you look at the complete
proposal it sketches how
um
the regulation of social behavior
depends on the learning of shared laws
and expectations
um and also how this connects to
utilizing cultural affordances
um and thinking through other Minds as
profits interactional property in which
agents learn to infer each other's
expectations to optimize Collective
behavior and decision making
okay so from these interesting active
inference and broader proposals of to
your mind to get to the issue of some
sophistication in active inference so
what is fear of my sophistication
um the short Recaps it's the depth of
recursivity that can be utilized for
serious mind of the form I think that
they think that I think
um
and it has been found that
agents generally use
a representative of between zero and
four
um and um that humans humans ability to
for recursive belief reasoning is
generally limiting
um but impressive performing this could
go on forever
um and one way to implement
this kind of sort of
uh arbitrarily recursive belief in
fairness
is composed by that at all
um we use the citation model of
sophisticated theory of mind
um with cape home agents and provide
stimulations in which Ketone agents take
as agents
um that are just one level of recursive
recursivity under them and this model
has been used for a lot of interesting
uh simulation experiments for example
um Divine at all
showed that in a trade-based analysis so
with agents have been fixed
um fixed steps of fear of mind
represivity
[Music]
um
there is a specific distribution of
Agents with level one time a level
two-tone and that could provide an
evolutionary Advantage compared to
populations with larger proportions of
serotonous fatal agents so they use they
look at being adaptive properties of
systems with different kinds of
ratios of
theory of my sophistication
um and in another
in another
experiments which is a state-based
analysis
um
for sure it all showed that if you use
computational signal typing or autistic
individuals
um they show this shows reduced
sensitivity to task framing
um and strategy switching within the
game that I've been using at the
required sophistication
and so these are just some interesting
applications for fear of my
sophistication and the promise of
modeling theory of my sophistication
would be that you could investigate how
people flexibly switch between different
social strategies while solving the
sexual tasks and one of them would be to
increase the depth of fear of line
sophistication or decreases depending
also on what you think about the other
the other agents sophistication
um
so what I've been working on at the
moment is an active inference model of
social prediction during the matching
pennies game
um the matching pennies game is a game
farm economics
um with a very simple format there are
two rules you have the guesser and the
Challenger the Challenger hides a penny
in one of the two hands the guest needs
to guess which hand if the guesser is
correct they win
um I think I guess it was wrong being
challenges
um this game has has some logical
equivalence
um one version of the game makes both of
the agent celex heads or tails so the
Challenger select heads or tails and the
getter to guess if it's heads or tails
but both have the same formal structure
um and
psychological experiments of subjects
performing this task have shown that
there is a strong social framing effect
in a matching penis game so participants
will be paved and it's full differently
depending on whether they're seeing that
they're playing against a human agent
versus
um an AI for example
um
additionally a comparison of Cape Town
and other computational strategies
um that were fitted on experimental data
of subjects playing the game revealed
that participants seem to reduce their
mind when playing game so there's a
strong indication that fear of Mind use
does their role in the matching pennies
scheme
um and that social framing will
um influence the social strategy that's
being employed by the players
um
so this is the very simple zero term
architecture for the matching pennies
game and I included beliefs about cell
choices
um as also kind of yeah monetary
self-states beliefs about other agents
choices on whether the Asian things the
uh the opposing agents agent has hidden
depending left or right
um and then the agent also tracks reward
States
um
since the game in the setting is device
in a way in which push the agents both
making observation simultaneously and
then all of the observations are
revealed
um this setup made sense
so just going to
drink a little water
um the outcome modalities of the
patients that the agents have are its
own choice observations
um the choice observations of the
opposite agent and the reward
observations and the possibilities there
the action space is very limited and the
seeker can choose to seek left or right
and The Hider which is the same as the
Challenger before
um has the possibility of hiding and
electoral rights and the reward is
uncontrollable since it depends on both
agents choices at the same time
um
yeah so this is sort of a a summary of
the architecture that I just described
and this is another visualization of
this setup and um
you can see here that if you look at the
likelihoods
um the reward mapping for the Seeker is
just the opposite as for the island
um and I think that this this simple
setup is uh very suited for uh studying
feared Minds in these kinds of simple
competitive uh uh interactions
okay so
um if you wanted to
um study the use of theory of my
sophistication in the matching pennies
game
um using active inference
uh I ran into a couple of challenges
um and one of them was how to
um
how to steer the problem of recurrence
so how can we make a difference between
the focal agents
um and the other agents if we try to
model the other ages within one agent
um especially if you want to introduce
or formalize depth of paper cresivity it
can't just make one agent stimulate the
other agents stimulating their cell
there needs to be some kind of sort of
um
structure that distinguishes sort of the
Soul's inferential mechanism and
self-learning mechanisms from what you
what the agent focal agent thinks the
other agent is uh thinking and seeing
and doom
um and I think the gentleman with the
bowler had by firster in 2003 is a good
example
um for this problem so you can
um that the basic setting is that our
world is populated by beings like
ourselves
um experience experiencing themselves as
a subject as the focal point of their
their worlds with their own thoughts and
feelings and they all think that they're
the one and only subject
um but in but their cons will be so
there needs to be sort of an either an
outside focal point
um or one ultimately subject
um and um yeah so I think more
practically the questions that arise
from this example are how do we
distinguish in focal agents and
stimulated agents
um and how can we simulate other agents
in a way that is computationally
efficient and maybe uses the same kinds
of resources that the agent already has
um
so I actually had a love meeting
um at the theoretical neurobiology lab a
while ago and we were brainstorming
about this issue
um and one of the ideas that came up was
to use sophisticated Insurance
um fourth year of mind
so in this case
um an active inference formulation of
the leaf repositivity could be used for
modeling recursive view of mind
um
and
um so basically the planning using
predictions about the other agents into
your class accounts would
um
consist of evaluating all the kinds of
hypothetical scenarios all kinds of
contextuals on how your actions like
influence their beliefs and their
actions and so on and so on
um
so this would be one bro to go into but
this would
also mean that all these conceptuals
will need to be evacuated
um so I was thinking is there a sort of
more efficient way
um
to sort of use these kinds of either
internal simulations or confessional
evaluation
um and the current uh approach I'm
working on
um which I've also sort of
um
yeah which I'm also still developing so
I'm very much open to feedback and
um comments on how this could work
um and possible alternative approaches
at this point
um but the general idea would be to
create a possible internal stimulation
of the other agents control mechanism so
taking the learning mechanism of an
active influence agent as sort of the
definition of what the focal agent is
that that is the agent that perceives
and learns and impairs from the
environment
um and
um what the agent does when predicting
the observations of the other agent or
the predicting the other agent's
behavior
um it's basically performing partial
simulation about what it thinks the
other agent's preferences are
um
and what it thinks that
um the other the other agent's strategy
is
um which is encoded by the transition
from state to state
um
and one of the potential ways in which
she could include recursivity in this
way is that you
um
pretend that you have control of the
other agent's actions and you predict
the other states you predict self-states
um it evaluates
um yeah you evaluate the state action
probabilities
um choose the most valuable
action based on the distribution
um simulates the other states that come
forth and simulate the self-states that
come forth
um and then you have a new
um
and then this can be used for
the next round of action selection by
the other model
um so in this case only the prior
preferences and the agent specific
transition probabilities would be
needed as sort of information on the
other agents and because you also want
to include some kind of learning about
the other strategies
um
one of the things you could Implement
would be
um learning also that they made
literacies and so having sort of a
specific uh the
um having the agents accumulative
evidence about this
transitions over time
um
to also better predict the other agent's
potential actions
um
so I asked sort of the basic principle
would be to simulate control from the
perspective of the other agents
um
and the recursivity comes into play when
you stimulate the other when you've
already simulated the others predicted
actions and predicted other states
and you've simulated your own actions as
a consequence of the stimulated actions
you can feed that back into the other
model to predict what they would do if
um they thought that you were in the
state that you were in
um and I think if you sort of uh yeah I
think that could be a
um
yeah a way to develop recursivity
um in a way that does not need complete
simulations of parallel agents within
the same system
um and of course there should be some
kind of temporal discounting so
parameter that discounts evidence based
on the simulated planning arising
um that is sort of yeah that is
um
that defines by the key number of steps
um so yeah this is sort of a conceptual
outline
um of how you could Implement uh
um recursive fear of Mind using active
inference
um we haven't been able to disclose the
Nations using this yet but we're working
on that and uh we're very
um much open to discussions on this and
Technical comments on how to improve on
this outline
um and one of sort of the the open
questions is still um that you're still
thinking about is how to make the agents
flexibly infer the depth of
repressibility of the other agents
um in the setting
um yeah Special thanks to uh Yong Dumas
who also be there at the panel I think
in session two
um we're super we're supervising me uh
during this project uh thanks to the
ppsp level I'm doing my internship to uh
really excite who's also working on a
related project uh the pi mdp team for
that great great coding package that I'm
using
um and for call First and for his
feedback and ideas on my previous
presentations
thank you very much for listening
oh
great presentation very um
comprehensive review of a lot of the
different theory of Minds
options out there
um well if anyone has questions they can
write it in a live chat what do you want
to explore or can I ask a question or or
what what would be fun for you
blinded by the lines at this point so
I'm not very
um I can't easily read from my screen so
maybe it would be nice if you could
um if you could read out the questions
that are in the live chat sure oh yeah
sure sure
um well first one one part I found
interesting you mentioned that people
play differently when they are playing a
human or when they believe that they're
playing a human so what is that
like what is the difference in play
when we believe that we're playing
another person
um
so as
so if I look at the original page where
um
there is one study on this and then
um they did the computational
stenotyping study using Cattlemen
alternative strategies
um and they showed that if you
use the social social framing condition
that subject will subjects will more
probably employ my strategy is compared
to other simple simple reward based
strategies
so maybe those strategies that should be
described using some kind of reward
learning mechanism
um but the difference in their overall
sort of trajectory of choices is I don't
know
yeah a few few themes then that you
brought up that came up earlier uh in
the session so one was using pi mdp and
sophisticated inference which Aspen Paul
gave a walk through on
and this question about recursivity and
about
the way in which
you can on one hand talk about
abstractly
like k recursivity
yet
the biological system doesn't implement
that kind of a logic and so so
um could you maybe describe a little bit
again how does the the structure that
you laid out for the generative model
capture some of those features of
recursivity without
falling into the Trap of um
just theory of mind all the way down
yes so my general idea was to simulate
the other agent's action prediction
um based on uh learning about the
transition
um probabilities for the other for our
sort of
what we think the other
um how the other agents stays
transitioned
um and then if you
um you've predicted what the other
Asians would do to do you can use that
as a prior for calculating
um action dependent uh expected States
and based on those evaluating those
expected States
um we have your who stimulate your own
choice mechanism
um
and I think in principle you could
use this recursive simulation
um indefinitely
but also yeah
it's also device in a way that it uses
the same kind of
um the same kind of sort of just the
architecture of the local agent so the
other idea was to just use internal
simulations all the way down
um
but that would yeah that would be very
comfortably impossible
um
and yeah I think it's a very good
question because how why would you even
need to formalize belief requestivity
all the way down if
in end effects um it will only use
Tom with the with the sets sort of
Maximum depth
and the fact that we use theory of mind
with a maximum death might also be sort
of a hint that he might also use
um a different or
what we do might also be described by a
different strategy
so I yeah I'm not sure if that's an
answer to your question
yeah well when I saw this and some of
the other generative models um you
mentioned maybe here like you pretend
like you can control the other person's
mind
and that's kind of the fundamental
weaving of action into the inference
Challenge and then that
uses expected free energy well just like
any other policy selection so it's like
pragmatic value would be bringing that
controllable State your your uh social
Partners mind your beliefs bringing them
into alignment with your preferences is
pragmatic and then learning more about
them is epistemic and so then that might
enable some theory of mind like Behavior
where it's like when you don't know
enough to put the squeeze on then you
have a kind of
open-ended learning and curiosity and
question driven theory of mind but then
once one has enough to kind of exploit
rather than explore then without
necessarily even updating the model or
engaging any like deeper recursivity or
strategic shifting you could get
um social behavior that's oriented
towards
control and pragmatic value rather than
just like learning and questioning
yeah I think you're you're very very the
idea was also to enable the agent to
um maybe first few strategies that are
more useful in
um Gathering evidence about the kinds of
strategies that the other agent is using
before exploiting
um what you've learned about the other
region
hmm
so what are your next steps with the
work
um so I think yeah right now the main
task would be to implement this using pi
mdp
and see if there are any sort of
formal for climates that I need to make
well in the implementation because it's
yeah if you can't build the two cons you
don't understand it so
um that's what I'm yeah that's what I'm
working on right now and then the next
step would be to introduce
um a mechanism to sort of maybe very
um
uh recursivity
um based on what the agent infers the
kind of recursivity the other region has
um but before that I also want to want
to use the model to perform
computational phenotyping
um
subjects that were doing the matching
honey sauce
and had different kinds of diagnoses so
there were neurotypical
um Youth and
um youth with
um youth on the ocean spectrum and
things with ADHD and anxiety and it
would be interesting to see if there is
any sort of difference in the depth of
repressivity that they employ as sort of
the flexibility with which they switch
between strategies
hmm
that makes me think about different
different levels or or differentials
between self-knowledge and other
knowledge
on one hand
we seem to know a lot about ourselves
but also
were often unaware or blind to
some some features or regularities of
ourselves that that might be highly
attended to by others
and so when we're rolling out these
games or scenarios there might be some
theory of Mind settings where like
knowing yourself better carries the day
but other settings where knowing like
the game is what matters or knowing the
partner in an iterated Game Theory or
like just knowing having a lot of
experience
um like there's a lot of
a lot of degrees of freedom
in modeling these very
um advanced
cognitive ecosystems
yeah I think that's also one of the
reasons that we chose the matching
pennies paradigm
because the Paradigm itself is very
simple what we're trying to model is
quite complicated
and on the matching pennies like
um so it's in one hand you know the
person has two hands behind the back and
then they bring out the two fists and
you're trying to guess like where it is
yeah and then I wondered well what if it
was you have to guess where it isn't
on one hand that's like kind of the same
or like if you say well you win when you
pick it
but then if you say well you win when
you when you pick the empty hand
mathematically it should be like the
same because knowing where one is is
like knowing where it isn't but but just
as a human game player
it has a very different feel
and those kinds of like
um reversals might give us insight into
our priors that support
not just open-ended abstract theory of
mind but like kind of with a lean
towards being pro-social
or like heuristics in place that that
support making
um quick decisions together
maybe rather than I I don't know
yeah I think those are all very good
um yeah
very very
um
sort of promising trains of thoughts I
just I think in the case in which you
you need to think the empty hand we
might have very strong sort of
um
beliefs about what if what or we might
experience sort of be a presence of
something as more inherently more
rewarding than the absence of something
because we have all these associations
with gifts and
getting things and like rewards are
usually things that are there
so I can imagine that in this case sort
of the perceived you would you wouldn't
perceive it as rewarding but formally it
would be completely the same
yeah yeah like uh receiving a benefit
versus averting a loss
yeah and then how that plays in and and
and our encultured
priors
and our our personal histories and how
these very deep layers of of
differences
might play out
and uh what kinds of empirical data or
online data
could could help us
generate like unique explanations or
predictions maybe situations like you
said some situations where a
reward-based model might be sufficient
but then I think the interesting
question for active people is like
where's the unique explanation or
prediction
that that really
um has active shine
and shows where surprise bounding as an
imperative gives us like more realistic
or more concise or conciliate
explanations in a way that like it
doesn't even make sense to appeal to
reward
yeah
yeah I think that's also the tricky bit
about this Paradigm is that it's very
much
I mean it's for war based in a sense but
I think because you have this social
framing effect you also have these
interesting learning mechanisms
um and mechanisms of uncertainty
reduction
that might play out in how the
um the agents behave in the end
but that's why we saw that it would
still be interesting to use active
inference to explore this Paradigm but
on the other hand I think if you on the
moment at the moment you're looking at
individual variation
um you might get interesting differences
in verbal sensitivity or
a version of yeah risk aversion stuff
like that
um that might be better expert in a
different context
oh any last comments or or thoughts
um
no yeah thank you for uh for your
comments and your uh
uh insights
yeah it's awesome it's a great Direction
happy to see it
all right
thanks everybody for presenting in this
first interval and
see you in the second interval
bye
thank you bye